<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon against halting betweene two opinions preached at S. Martins in the fields, By Iohn Seller, Bacheler in Diuinitie</title>
            <author>Seller, John, 1592 or 3-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113727</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848958</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848958</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14083</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11882)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14083)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1463:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon against halting betweene two opinions preached at S. Martins in the fields, By Iohn Seller, Bacheler in Diuinitie</title>
                  <author>Seller, John, 1592 or 3-1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 53, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Creede, for William Welbie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 21 and 53 misnumbered 13 and 35.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁴ H³.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14083:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GAINST HALTING BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TWEENE TWO OPINI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; preached at <hi>S. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins</hi> in the fields, BY IOHN SELLER, BACHELER IN DIVINITIE.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by Thomas Creede, for William Welbie. 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14083:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14083:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, AND MY VERY HONORABLE GOOD LORDE <hi>George,</hi> Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterburie</hi> his Grace, Primate and Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane of all England.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may ſeeme ſtrange (moſt reuerend, and mine honourable good Lorde) that in this learned age of the world, wherin the truth of Ieſus Christ hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo cleare a light, and that God of his mercie hath reſtored the Goſpell vnto vs, &amp; cauſed the beames thereof to ſhine ouer all Countreys, in ſuch ſort, as now the ſimple, the vnlearned, the rich, the learned, the worſhipful, the Honorable, the States and Princes of the world are become the Profeſſors,<note place="margin">D. Biſhop in his Epiſtle De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatorie to the King.</note> and maintainers of it, there ſhould notwithſtanding, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this kingdome remaine ſuch a number of recuſant Papiſts, as the Papiſts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues haue made their crakes and vaunt, ſtiling them all, with the name of Dutifull and well deſeruing Subiects. How Dutifull ſubiects they haue bene, <hi>quid audiam verb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ùm videa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facta?</hi> Let the ſundrie intended inuaſions againſt this Kingdome, and forraine practiſes abroad, procured onely by their meanes: let their trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous, and rebellious enterpriſes, their piuate plottes, machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, poiſonings, murthers, let the pouder treaſon, the eternall ſhame of that murtherous and bloodie generation, the memorie of which moſt deteſtable and damnable fact, all the <hi>indices ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgatorij</hi> in the world ſhal neuer be able to blot out, make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to all the Chriſtian world, how vniuſtly, and vntrulie they challenge to themſelues the name of dutifull and faithfull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects,
<pb facs="tcp:14083:3"/> whoſe deadly hatred and vnnaturall practiſes againſt our Church and Common-weale, haue proued by many degrees far more dangerous, then euer were the practiſes, and plottes, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions of that curſed ſeede of the Cananites, Ammonites, and Iebuſites againſt the ſtate and gouernment of the Iſraelites, the choſen people of God. Touching the number of recuſant papiſts in other ſhires, I haue no great skill: it may be, it is greater in tale then it is in ſtrength. But howſoeuer it be, the greater the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, the greater danger accrueth both to the Prince &amp; ſtate of this Land. Onely thus much I may truly affirme, that if all the Prouince of Canterbury were as free from that leproſie and contagious infection of Poperie, as is the Dioceſe of Canterbury, the Papiſts ſhould haue ſmall cauſe to make their boaſt &amp; crakes of <hi>ſo many &amp; ſo manie.</hi> For whereas there are in the Dioceſe of Canterburie &amp; Rocheſter, ſome <hi>398.</hi> pariſhes, betweene <hi>90.</hi> &amp; an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred thouſand co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municants, there were not (as I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry crediblie enformed) found of record the laſt aſſiſe aboue the number of ten recuſant papiſts. So that thus much I may truly report, for the honour of the Countie of Kent, that as in the time of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> they alone were in his iudgement of all the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, accompted to be <hi>omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> humaniſſimi:</hi> and in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt reputed to be <hi>omnium bellicoſiſſimi,</hi> &amp; therefore as <hi>Geruaſius</hi> affirmeth by a prehemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in right of their manhode challenged to themſelues the foreward of all bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells, as of right belonging vnto them, becauſe they were the onely people of the land, that were neuer vanquiſhed by the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, but yeelded themſelues by compoſition: euen ſo at this day, conſidering the ſmall number of recuſants, &amp; withall, the great number of reuerend Preachers and Paſtors disperſed ouer all the Countrey, men furniſhed and qualified with very rare and excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t gifts, for the worke of the miniſtery, they may deſerued<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be reputed, <hi>omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fideliſſimi:</hi> the moſt loyall and faithfull ſubiects of this kingdome. A large proofe of whoſe fidelitie, the late Queene of moſt bleſſed and happy memorie, found in her greateſt need, when vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſuddain arriuall of the Spaniſh ſhips vpon our Seas, by the pollicie and vigilancie of S. Thomas Scot,
<pb facs="tcp:14083:3"/> being then one of the Deputy Lieutena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for thoſe parts (a knight of whome I can neither ſpeake nor write without much honour, there were gathered together within the ſpace of <hi>24.</hi> houres, the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of eight thouſand valiant fighting men, ready to encounter the enemie. At which time there were ſundry preachers of vs in that Camp, ſome preaching on our horſe-backes, ſome vpon the tops of trees, others in pulpits made of turfe, where we might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and ſee that huge Armado of Spaine, whome the Pope had bleſſed, &amp; chriſtned, by the name of the inuincible Nauie, which in very few daies after, how it fell from an vnmeaſurable high ioy to an vnmeaſurable deep diſpaire, their great caſtles of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort being ouerthrowne, and brought to the ground: I neede not further relate, the ſtorie thereof being yet freſh in the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of many thouſands liuing this day.</p>
            <p>This which I haue here ſet downe for the honour of our Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh people, I haue written it partly to note one ſpeciall ſweet fruit of the Goſpel, whereſoeuer it hath free paſſage; that is, that it ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth the hearts of all that ſincerely profeſſe it, with fidelity, loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, and all manner Chriſtian ſubiection to the higher powers.</p>
            <p>Partly againe, that it may adde ſome incouragement to your Gra: the more willingly (as leiſure &amp; oportunity ſhall fit) to come among vs, ſpecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your Grace ſhal come to a people ſo ciuil, and ſo ingenuous, ſo kind, &amp; ſo religious, and ſo louing, and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue of their Dioceſan, as no one countrey of this Kingdome can afford vs the like preſident. Which to be true, the late moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy B: mine old Maiſter, B: Whitgift, of moſt learned, &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly memorie, found by good proofe, at his firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming downe into Kent, whom the whole Gentrie of that Dioceſe entertained, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then the <hi>Galathians</hi> did the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paule:</hi> that is, <hi>like an Angell of God,</hi> with ſuch obſequiouſnes, eſteeme, and reuerence as was fitting for the condition and ſtate of ſo graue a Biſhop, and ſo worthy a Prelate.</p>
            <p>As for vs both of the Laitie and Clergie of your Graces Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſe, as wee haue great cauſe of reioycing offered vnto vs all, to ſtirre vs vp to a thankefull congratulation of your Lor: late de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued preferment, &amp; withall, to magnifie the great goodneſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:14083:4"/> God towardes vs, in that hee hath aduanced your Grace to that height of honour, to make your Grace a glorious inſtrument of much good to this Church of England, the charge and gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof, next vnder our gracious Soueraigne, is principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie committed; So for mine owne particular, conſidering the continuall flowe of thoſe manifolde fauours your Grace hath bene pleaſed to ſhewe vnto mee, which with all due thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, I moſt willingly acknowledge, hauing no other meanes out of my ſmall fortunes to doe you honour, I haue preſumed in a Chriſtian boldneſſe, by way of Dedication, to offer this paper preſent vnto your Grace, a Sermon which this laſt moneth I preached before a very honourable, worſhipfull, and a moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and religious auditorie of the pariſh of S. Martins in the fieldes. Thus preſuming (as you ſee) of your Graces accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and bolde dedicating this ſmall and ſimple diſcourſe vnto your Grace, which I confeſſe to be much vnworthy your worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I will not ceaſe to pray vnto God to requite, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence ſeuenfolde into your boſome, both this, and all other your vndeſerued fauours towards me. And thus beſeeching the God of heauen and earth againe and againe, to multiplie his richeſt bleſſings and mercies towards you, by giuing you honour here, and honour euer, in his happie Kingdome of eternall comfort, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces humbly deuoted Chaplin, in all dutie to be commanded. <hi>Iohn Seller.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14083:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO MY CHRISTIAN AVDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> of S. <hi>Martins</hi> in the fields.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued in the Lord, this <hi>Sermon</hi> was lately preached in your pariſh; it is now to be acted (if I may ſay ſo) vpon a <hi>Theater;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theatrum mundus.</note> &amp; I am intreated (as it were a prologue) to ſay vnto you, <hi>Come and ſee.</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.46.</note> I need not to doe it, for you, who are carefull to come and heare, will (I hope) be as carefull to come &amp; ſee. Come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I beſeech you, and behold another <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> in the ſpirit of <hi>Elias,</hi> preparing in your harts a way for the Lord:<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 3.4.</note> and ſaying vnto you as God ſaith to all, <hi>This is the way, walke in it.</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 30.21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Are you deſirous of a guide in this way? here are two offering of themſelues, God &amp; <hi>Baal;</hi> the one will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct you to the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 1.2.</note> the other will lead you blindfold to <hi>Samaria</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 6.19.</note>. If you follow the one, you wil worſhip in mount <hi>Zion;</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ.</hi> 2.2.3.</note> If the other you, muſt goe vp to mount <hi>Gerizim;</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.20.</note> and there adore <hi>Ieroboams</hi> calues,<note n="(h)" place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 12.28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This latter is a way pleaſing now a daies to many, <hi>but the iſſues thereof are the waies of death?</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 14.12.</note> And when the paſſing bell calleth, there is ſo litle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort in that paſſage, that many, who haue gone it, forſake it at the laſt.</p>
            <p>I reade of a learned popiſh doctor in <hi>Germanie,</hi> who at the howre of his death, entring into a meditation of the inſufficiencie of his merits, cried out after this manner,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Selnec Inſtit. pag. <hi>386.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alas what ſhall I now doe? No workes doe me any good; none comfort me; none cheare me; Since then I finde nothing
<pb facs="tcp:14083:5"/> in myſelfe to ſtay vpon, this will I doe; Haue mercy vpon me O Lord, for thy ſonne Chriſts ſake, and receiue my ſoule.</hi> It is the ſafeſt way as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſſeth, and the onely way, as the ſcripture proueth.</p>
            <p>Looke not then vpon <hi>Baal</hi> with his 450. falſe Prophets;<note n="(l)" place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 18.22.</note> but looke vpon God with his ſeruant <hi>Eliah.</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 18.30.</note> 
               <hi>Baal</hi> as an <hi>Vlyſses</hi> will transforme you; as a <hi>Syren</hi> ſeduce you; as an <hi>Helena</hi> corrupt you; and as <hi>Naaſh</hi> the <hi>Ammonite</hi> make no couenant with you, vnles he may plucke out your right eye of knowledge, and ſo bring a ſhame vpon <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Our God is not like their God, our aduerſaries being iudges.<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.31.</note> He is our ſunne,<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11.</note> without him it is night: our ſtarre,<note n="(q)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 2.28.</note> without him it is darknes, our life,<note n="(r)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.25.</note> without him it is death; and our guide, without him wee ſhall neuer make our pathes ſtraight.<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 25 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is better to limpe in the ſtrait waies of God, then to runne and rampe on in the broad pathes of <hi>Baal;</hi> you know theſe things, happie are ye if ye doe them.<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.17.</note> In a word, learne by this godly treatiſe, to deteſt that faith, not of Ieſus, but of the Ieſuites, which teacheth, that you muſt eate your God; and may kill your <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Qui cum Ieſu itis, non itis cum Ieſuitis,</q>
            <q>
               <l>You that doe follow Ieſus trace,</l>
               <l>will neuer like the Ieſuites pace.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The Lord make you as beautifull in the eyes of God, as you haue made your Church to the eyes of man. </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aprill.</hi> 16. 1611.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your ancient ſeruant in the Lord,</hi> Robert Hill.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14083:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GAINST HALTING betweene two opinions.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1.</hi> King: Cap: <hi>18.</hi> Ver. <hi>20.</hi> &amp; <hi>21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> So <hi>Ahab</hi> ſent to all the children of Iſraell, and gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Prophets together to Mount <hi>Carmel:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> And <hi>Elias</hi> came to all the people, and ſaide, how long halt ye betweene two opinions? If the Lord be God follow him: If <hi>Baal</hi> be hee, goe after him. And the people anſwered him not one word.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong other bleſſings which God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth vpon his Church, a good Prince is one of the greateſt, being ſet ouer his people, for the defence and maintenance of true religion and vertue. And for this cauſe it is, that the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paule</hi> willeth vs, firſt and aboue all other things, to pray <hi>for Kings, and for all that are in authoritie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>that [vnder them] we may leade a quiet and peaceable life, in all godlines and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</hi> In the which words the Apoſtle ſetteth downe three ſpeciall good things which wee enioy vnder the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a godlie and religious Prince; namely, godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, honeſtie, and peace, which being ioyned together, are the onely ſupporters and vpholders of all Chriſtian Common-wealths and Kingdomes: but being ſeuered one from an other, there falleth out a cleane contrarie
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14083:6"/> ſequele. For what is godlines without honeſtie, but plaine hypocriſie? or what is honeſtie without godlines, but meere heathniſh gentilitie? or what is peace without honeſtie and godlines, but carnall ſecuritie? Now as for honeſtie and godlines without peace, there can bee no great practiſe of either of them both.</p>
            <p>It was a great hindrance to the people of Iſrael in their deuotions, when by the crueltie of <hi>Pharao</hi> they might not be permitted to goe into the wildernes to ſerue God. And afterwards in the captiuity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſing the Lords ſong in a ſtrange land: Peace and tranquilitie are euer an occaſion of great increaſe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification. In the <hi>Acts</hi> when the Churches had reſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout all <hi>Iudea</hi> and <hi>Galilie,</hi> and <hi>Samaria, they were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts,</hi> 9.31.</note> 
               <hi>and walked in the feare of the Lorde, and were multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the comfort of the holie Ghoſt.</hi> Where wee may ſee how in a quiet and peaceable Church, daily teaching and preaching is of verie great force to plant godlines and the feare of God in mens hearts, and withall, diſcipline of manners: whereas in a Church which is vnder the croſſe, it falleth out ſtill for the moſt part, that eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call aſſemblies are hindered and forbidden to be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Miniſters and Preachers are either impriſoned, dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen away, or put to death: Parents, and fathers of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies driuen away out of their houſes; whereby ſuch hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes being diſſolued, children are bereaued of good edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, godlie men are ſeuered one from another: in which diſſipation ſound doctrine is not to be had: Faith languiſheth: all godly exerciſes in training vp of youth lieth ſtill, and all other godlie and Chriſtian meetings quite geuen ouer: Farre otherwiſe then it was vnder the raignes of <hi>Dauid, Ezechias, Ioſias</hi> and <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> in whoſe dayes the people enioyed thoſe three bleſſings before remembred; namely, godlines, honeſtie, and peace. All thoſe godly and religious Kings, not onely by words en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the people to ſerue God, but by their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14083:6"/> drawing great multitudes to imitate the ſame zeale and feruencie, which they ſaw to be in ſuch Princes vnder whom they liued. But on the other ſide, when God in his anger and iuſt indignation ſendeth wicked Princes to ſit in place of iudgement and authoritie, religion and vertue goeth to decay, Gods honour is defaced, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple drawne to idolatrie, the worſhip and ſeruice of God prophanely abuſed: the truth whereof as it appeareth by diuerſe and ſundry examples of wicked Kings in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſcriptures, ſo in none more plainly then in <hi>King Ahab,</hi> of whome I ſhall haue occaſion heereafter to ſpeake, of whom the Scripture thus recordeth, <hi>that he ſolde himſelfe to doe wickedly in the ſight of the Lord, that hee did exceeding abhominably in following idolles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>King:</hi> 10.30.31.</note> 
               <hi>according to allthat the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites did,</hi> being prouoked thervnto by <hi>Iezabel</hi> his wife. <hi>For it was a light thing for him to walk in the ſinnes of Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, except he tooke</hi> Iezabel <hi>alſo the daughter of</hi> Ethbaal, <hi>king of the</hi> Sydonians <hi>to wife, and ſerued</hi> Baal, <hi>and worſhipped him.</hi> In whoſe dayes what an hauocke there was made of the Saintes and ſeruants of God, what an increaſe there was made of moſt groſſe idolatrie, by ioyning Gods worſhip and <hi>Baals</hi> together; what ſlaughter of the Prophets of God liuing in thoſe times, <hi>which went vp and downe, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering in ſheepes-skinnes and goates skinnes, beeing deſtitute, tormented, and afflicted;</hi> and for the ſafegard of their liues, being glad to <hi>wander in the wilderneſſe and mountaines, and dennes and caues of the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb:</hi> 11.37.</note> is plainely to be ſeene by the complaint and requeſt of the Prophet,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King:</hi> 19.14.</note> which hee made vnto God againſt Iſrael, ſaying, <hi>O Lorde the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael haue forſaken thy couenant, caſt downe thine Altars, and ſlaine thy Prophet with the ſworde, and I onely am left, and they ſeeke my life to take it away.</hi> (Albeit the anſwer of God <hi>ſaid vnto him, I haue reſerued to my ſelfe ſeuen thouſand men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom:</hi> 11.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>which haue not bowed the knee to Baal:</hi>) In this great and miſerable deſolation, and confuſion of his Church, the Lord remembring his people of Iſrael, when they little
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14083:7"/> looked for it, and leſſe deſerued it, ſent <hi>Elias</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet vnto them, who, the more forciblie to drawe both the King and his Subjects to a ſerious conſideration of their ſinnes, and to ſhew how greatly the Lord was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed for their idolatrous worſhipping of <hi>Baal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>King:</hi> 17.1.</note> tolde king <hi>Ahab</hi> to his face, <hi>As the Lorde liueth, before whome I ſtand, there ſhall be neither deaw nor raine theſe yeares, but according to my word:</hi> which indeed according to the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Prophet came to paſſe. For as <hi>Elias</hi> (moued by the inſtinct of Gods holy ſpirit) prayed vnto God <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly that it might not raine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam:</hi> 5.17.</note> ſo according to his prayer, it <hi>rained on the earth, for three yeares and ſixe moneths.</hi> By meanes wherof, the famine was ſo great in <hi>Iſrael</hi> for lacke of raine, that man and beaſt were readie to periſh: and raine they could haue none but at <hi>Elias</hi> word, as <hi>Elias</hi> had told the king before the drought beganne. At the ende of the three yeares and ſixe moneths of drought,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King:</hi> 18.1.</note> the Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> was commaunded <hi>to ſhewe himſelfe to king Ahab,</hi> and albeit hee was greatly diſſwaded ſo to doe by <hi>Obadiah,</hi> whom hee met in the way, yet the Prophet was reſolute, ſolemnly proteſting to <hi>Obadiah, As the Lord of Hostes liueth, in whoſe preſence I ſtand, I will ſurely ſhew my ſelfe vnto Ahab this day.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>King:</hi> 18: 15.</note> Meeting therfore with <hi>Ahab,</hi> and beeing challenged by him as the author of that famine, and troubler of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he diſcharged himſelfe, and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted before the King, that God plagued the whole Land, becauſe hee and his Fathers houſe had forſaken the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of the Lord, and followed other Gods. And to iuſtifie his ſpeech, he offered to prooue before all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> on the danger of his owne head, that the king and the Land were but ſeduced and abuſed by the Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> and that hee would prooue by no worſe meanes then by miraculous fire from heauen, which ſhould ſhew them whoſe ſacrifice was accepted, aſſuring them of raine aboundantly after their conuerſion to the true GOD, for which cauſe at this time hee was ſent vnto them.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14083:7"/>
            <p>To this the King gaue his conſent, and by the perſwaſion and motion of <hi>Elias,</hi> ſent by his Princely authoritie, for all Iſrael, that they ſhould gather themſelues together in mount <hi>Carmel,</hi> together with the Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> 450. (which were diſperſed throghout all the tribes of Iſrael,) the prophets of the groues, 400. which did eat at <hi>Iezabels</hi> table. The King, &amp; the chiefe heads of the people of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, and the prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> being thus aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in mount <hi>Carmel, Elias</hi> commeth to the people, and ſaith thus vnto them; <hi>How long will yee halt betweene two Opinions, &amp;c?</hi> In the which words of the Prophet, I obſerue foure ſpeciall things worthy of conſideration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diuiſio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, he reproueth the Iſraelites for their halting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences betweene two religions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, hee declareth vnto them that they cannot ſerue both <hi>Baal</hi> and God together, and that religion is not a thing indifferent.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdlie, hee exhorteth them to conſtancie in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in following of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthlie, the ſucceſſe which followed this reproofe of the Prophet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the reproofe of the Prophet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I obſerue theſe foure points.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, who it is that reproueth, <hi>Elias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondlie, the perſons whom he doth reproue; The people of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdlie, the perſon before whom: King <hi>Ahab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthlie, the thing he reproueth in the people: their wauering and vnconſtancie in matter of religion.</p>
            <p>In the perſon of <hi>Elias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The perſon of Elias.</note> wee haue to obſerue the great zeale, conſtancie, and boldneſſe, which ſhould bee in the miniſters and preachers of the Goſpel. For vnto them it belongeth to preach the preachings the Lorde hath bidden them, and to proclaime his vengeance againſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14083:8"/> ſinners, yea euen to ſtand at the gates of paradiſe with a flaming ſword in their mouth againſt obſtinate and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repentant ſinners. That which the prophet Micheas ſaith of himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mich.</hi> 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>that he was full of power by the ſpirit of the Lord, and of iudgement, and of ſtrength, to declare vnto Iacob his tranſgreſſion, and to Iacob his ſinne,</hi> was as truly verified in his owne perſon whom neither the Courtlike perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Eunuch that went for him, nor the conſent of 400. Prophets, nor the fauour of two Kings, nor the danger of his owne head could driue him from the word of God: And when the Eunuch had ſaid vnto him, <hi>behold now the words of the Prophets declare good things vnto the King with one accord:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 22.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>let thy word therefore, I pray thee be like vnto the word of one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſpeake thou good,</hi> Micheas anſwered him roundly, <hi>As the Lord liueth, whatſoeuer the Lord ſaith vnto me, that will I ſpeake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like zeale and courage we reade in Scripture to haue beene in <hi>Elizeus</hi> the Prophet, vnto whom when King <hi>Iehoram, Ahabs</hi> ſon had ſent to know of him what ſucceſſe his battell intended againſt the King of <hi>Moab</hi> was like to haue, the Prophet very boldly anſwered the King after this manner; <hi>What haue I to doe with thee? get thee to the Prophets of thy Fathers, and to the Prophets of thy mother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 3.13.14.</note> and ſaid moreouer vnto him, <hi>as the Lord liueth, in whoſe ſight I ſtand, if it were not that I regarde the preſence of</hi> Iehoſaphat <hi>the king of</hi> Iudah, <hi>I would not once haue looked towardes thee nor ſeene thee.</hi> But of all others commended in ſcripture for zeale and courage, the prophet <hi>Elias</hi> may carie the praiſe from them al: Of whom in Eccleſiaſticus it is thus reported,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſt. cap.</hi> 48.1.</note> 
               <hi>that he ſtood like a fire, and his words burned like a lampe, and becauſe the people of</hi> Iſrael <hi>could not away with the commandement of the Lord, by the word of the Lord he ſhut the heauen, and ſo brought a famine vpon them. He was appointed to reproue in due ſeaſon, and to pacifie the wrath of the Lords iudgement before it kindled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Malac.</hi> 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo to turne the hearts of the Fathers to the children, and the hearts
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14083:8"/> of the children to their fathers.</hi> Vnto the which place the Angell <hi>Gabriel</hi> propheſying before hand vnto <hi>Zacharie,</hi> what manner of perſon his ſonne <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> ſhould be, alludeth, ſaying;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>that he ſhould goe before the Lord in the power and ſpirit of</hi> Elias, <hi>to turne the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the diſobedient to the wiſedome of the iuſt, to make readie a people prepared for the Lord.</hi> O that all the Preachers and Miniſters of this kingdome were ſo poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with the power and ſpirit of <hi>Elias,</hi> that by beating downe ſinne and wickedneſſe, by the ſword of the ſpirit, and by giuing knowledge of ſaluation to the people of God, they might prepare the waies of the Lord by pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe the mountaines, by raiſing and filling vp the vallies, by making crooked things ſtraight, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king rough waies ſmooth; <hi>By the mountaines are vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, men that are very high and proud in the opinion of their owne righteouſnes, which by the preaching of the Goſpell ſhall abate their pride, and ſo come to Chriſt. By the vallies are meant, men that are vtterly deſpaire of all men, and altogether liuing in diſpaire: ſuch ſhalbe raiſed vp to the fellowſhip and communion of the kingdome of heauen: By crooked things are ſignified ſuch things as haue beene warped and writhed ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie waies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9.</note> 
               <hi>which ſhall be made ſtraight by the leuell and ſquire of the Goſpell. For how ſhall a young man (ſaith Dauid) clenſe his waies, but by ruling himſelfe after the word of God. As for the rough waies that ſhalbe made plaine, they are called rough by reaſon of the thornes of manifold vices, and naughtie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and luſts, the ſhort is, that the courſe of all things ſhalbe changed to ſuch contraries, that all impediments and lettes that ſhall hinder the courſe of the Goſpell, ſhall be broken, and ſo the Preachers of Chriſts ſacred word &amp; Goſpel, ſhall make readie a people prepared for the Lord.</hi> But alas we are fallen into theſe miſerable daies, euen the worſt and laſt daies, that we are ſo farre off from ſuffering ourſelues to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued when we ſinne, that we doe reioyce when we doe wickedly.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14083:9"/>
            <p>Wee cannot abide to haue our faults touched. Our Pride is growen as high as the Heauen: our couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is ſunke as deepe as hell; and yet wee cannot in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſe ſuffer ourſelues to be reproued. Wee ſay to the preachers, Peace, and talke not vnto vs in the name of the Lord; tell not vs of the Scripture: Tell not vs of Chriſt, of <hi>Peter,</hi> of <hi>Paul:</hi> wee bid the preacher ſpeake vs faire, and we bid him bleſſe thoſe things, which are accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Gods owne mouth. Nay, manie there are which are already wearie of the Goſpel, and wearie of their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, they call them Pulpit-men of the ſpirite, Prieſts, and I know not what, as though themſelues had nothing to doe with the ſpirite of God. They ſay the Preacher is too buſie, hee medleth with that he knoweth not. Yes, thou fooliſh man, he knoweth it well enough. He know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that pride is pride: that extortion is extortion: that couetouſnes is couetouſnes: that ſacriledge is ſacriledge: that vſurie is vſurie: that ſinne is ſinne: and thou, and thine owne conſcience knoweth it too, if thou wouldeſt be knowen of it.</p>
            <p>But God is iuſt, and as the extreme diſdaine of Gods truth, and his holie Goſpel, deſerueth the extremitie of Gods vengeance; So can it not bee without ſpeedie, and earneſt repentance, but that this Goſpel, that we are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſo wearie of, ſhall bee taken away from vs; euen the kingdome of God, which is the true vnderſtanding of Gods word, ſhall be taken away from vs: And then, what can there remaine, but blindneſſe and ignorance, which is the kingdome of the diuell.</p>
            <p>But this is the only comfort that Preachers haue in this great contradiction and oppoſition of the worlde, that if they haue a carefull endeuour to diſcharge a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in crying out againſt wickedneſſe: and lifting vp their voices, like a Trumpet againſt the diſorders of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon life, God Almightie will ſo arme all ſuch zealous preachers, with ſuch an inuincible ſtrength and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14083:9"/> that all the powers of the world ſhall neuer be able to ouercome them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bee not afraide,</hi> (ſaith God to the Prophet <hi>Ieremie) of their faces, for beholde</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>I haue this day made thee a defenced citie, and an iron pillar, and walles of braſſe againſt the whole land, againſt the kings of</hi> Iuda, <hi>and againſt the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces therof,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>againſt the Prieſts therof &amp; againſt the people of the land. They ſhall fight againſt thee, but they ſhall not preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee. For I am with thee, to deliuer thee,</hi> ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>What ſaith <hi>S. Cyprian, Shall the inuincible Tents of Chriſt, defended with the ſtrength of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt. ad Cornel:</note> 
               <hi>giue place to the terrors and threatnings of men? Shall the Church yeeld to the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tol? Shall the outrages of madde men be greater then the iudgements and cenſures of miniſters?</hi> No, God forbid, it muſt not be ſo. For, are not the preachers the lights of the world, and therefore appointed by God to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie faultes? are they not the voice of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt?</hi> why then ſhould not they crie out againſt ſinnes? Seeing therefore, they are the ſeers of the Lorde, they muſt not be blinde: and being the Lords criers, they muſt not be dumbe, nor tongue-tyed. And thus much touching the perſon of <hi>Elias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the perſon of king <hi>Ahab,</hi> I note how ſtronglie and forciblie an euill example of a wicked Prince, draweth the people to imitate, and to make all the ſubjectes with whome they liue, as like vnto them in naughtineſſe, as Bees are like vnto Bees.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Regis ad exemplum totus componitur Orbis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee all knowe the force of Example, <hi>Like people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa:</hi> 24.2.</note> 
               <hi>like Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt: like ſeruant like Maiſter: like maide, like Mistris: like buyer, like ſeller: like lender, like borrower: like giuer, like taker to vſurie.</hi> So that the greater the example is, the greater autoritie it hath to draw to ſimilitude.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Abimelech</hi> cut downe his bough and bare it on his ſhoulder, then all the people did ſo and followed him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudi,</hi> 9.48. 1. <hi>King:</hi> 12.28.</note> When King <hi>Ieroboam</hi> made two golden Calues, no great
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14083:10"/> maruell if the people ſtraight-waies beganne to Sacrifice in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel. Dionyſius</hi> had no ſooner left off the ſtudy of <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> but all the Courtiers by and by gaue it ouer.</p>
            <p>Princes therefore, and ſuch as are placed in higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, had need to take heede, and diligently to beware how they ſinne the ſinne of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> which not onely ſinned himſelfe, but cauſed <hi>Iſraell</hi> to ſinne, and ſo binde two ſinnes together. The reaſon is, becauſe the verie credite, and countenance, and prioritie of their places, being ſo eminent, makes others the bolder to ſinne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſinne with ſuch actors. And yet this may ſeeme ſtrange in the corruption of mans nature, that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people are more eaſily giuen to follow their euill exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples and offences, then ready to take benefite of the good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of godly and religious Princes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron:</hi> 17.6.</note>
               <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> was a good king, <hi>who lifted vp his heart vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wayes of the Lorde, walking in the firſt wayes of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Dauid:</hi> yet was not his good example ſo potent and forcible to retaine his people in the profeſſion of the true worſhip and ſeruice of God, as the euill example of <hi>Ahab</hi> was of power to entice his Subiects to become worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of <hi>Baal</hi> the Idoll of the <hi>Sydonians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> in pollicie ioyned affinitie with <hi>Ahab,</hi> and gaue his Sonne in marriage vnto <hi>Athali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> daughter of <hi>Iezabel:</hi> beeing perſwaded that by this matche there would growe a perpetuall peace betweene the two kingdoms, being by blood ſo neerely conioined together; and withall, concerning an aſſured hope, by this means to reduce the ten Tribes to the true worſhip of the God which then flouriſhed in <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> he was decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, &amp; ſo farre off from attaining to his wiſhed and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ende, that the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſtood moſt ſtifflie in maintenance of their prieſt-mate idolatrie, and by their wicked exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, drew almoſt all <hi>Iuda</hi> to the ſame moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable worſhip of <hi>Baal. For as the ſtorie of the ſcripture
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14083:10"/> recordeth,</hi> Iehoſaphat <hi>was no ſooner dead, but</hi> Iehoram <hi>his ſonne by the counſell of wicked</hi> Athalia <hi>his wife, being placed in the kingdome of his father, and making himſelfe ſtrong, ſlew all his brethren with the ſword, and ſo continued to walke in the way of the kings of</hi> Iſrael,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 21.4.</note> 
               <hi>the reaſon whereof is ſet downe by the holy ghoſt, becauſe he had</hi> Athalia <hi>the daughter of</hi> Ahab <hi>to wife, but the Lord plaguea him, becauſe he made</hi> Iuda <hi>and the inhabitants of</hi> Ieruſalem <hi>to goe a whoring,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 21.13.</note> 
               <hi>as the houſe of</hi> Ahab <hi>went a whoring, and had ſlaine the brethren of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which were better then himſelfe. So that after many cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that befell</hi> Iehoram <hi>the king for his falling away from God, the Lord ſmote his bowelles with an incurable diſeaſe, and ſo after two yeares his guttes fell out with his diſeaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His ſonne</hi> Ahaziah <hi>partly moued by the example of his father to commit idolatrie; partly egged on by the perſwaſion of his mother</hi> Athalia, <hi>who counſelled him to doe wickedly, and principally chooſing onely ſuch to be his counſellers, which were of the houſe of</hi> Ahab, <hi>which were indeed to his deſtruction, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with</hi> Iehoram <hi>his vncle the ſonne of</hi> Ahab <hi>to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Hazael <hi>king of</hi> Aram, <hi>was ſlaine by the hands of</hi> Iehu, <hi>whom the Lord had annointed to deſtroy the houſe of</hi> Ahab, <hi>whoſe deſtruction</hi> came <hi>of the Lord, becauſe he ioyned himſelfe with goddes enemies. After his death</hi> Athalia <hi>ſeeing that her ſonne was dead, to the intent there ſhould remaine none of the royall progenie of</hi> Dauid, <hi>that ſhould make title and claime to the crowne and kingdome of</hi> Iuda, <hi>ſhe aroſe and deſtroyed all the kings ſeed of the houſe of</hi> Iuda. <hi>But God almightie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the couenant which he had made with</hi> Diuid, <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had made a promiſe to giue a light vnto him, and to his ſonnes for euer, ſtirred vp the heart of</hi> Iehoſhabeath <hi>the daughter of the king, and ſiſter of</hi> Ahaziah <hi>to commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who tooke</hi> Ioes <hi>the ſonne of</hi> Ahaziah, <hi>and ſtole him away from the kings ſonnes that ſhould be ſlaine, and put him and his nurſe in the bedchamber, and ſo by hiding of him in the houſe of God during thoſe ſixe yeares wherein</hi> Athaliah <hi>raigned ouer the land, preſerued his life.</hi> Thus we may ſee what it is for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14083:11"/> godly Princes to ioyne affinitie with the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and how quickly <hi>Iuda</hi> and the inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> were inticed and drawne to goe a whoring, as the houſe of <hi>Ahab</hi> went a whoring; whereas none of all the kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> could euer be drawne by the voyces of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of God ſent vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to worſhip the Lord in <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> which was the place, where the Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded his name to be called on. We reade how the Egyptians not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the people of God continued many yeares among them in Egypt, where they might ſee how God was truly to be worſhipped, yet for all their conuerſing with them, were litle or nothing the better for them: but plaine it is, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> after their departure from <hi>Egypt,</hi> did many yeares after ſmell of the leuen of <hi>Egypt,</hi> where they ſaw before their eyes both calues, ſheepe, and oxen worſhipped in ſtead of gods, which cauſed them many times to commit moſt groſſe, &amp; abominable ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, the reaſon why the nature of man is ſo pliable to learne all manner of wickedneſſe (for <hi>dociles imitandis turpibus &amp; prauis omnes ſumus</hi>), is becauſe the nature of ſinne is ſuch, ſo potent &amp; ſtrong, that eaſily and quickly, it creepeth, and corrupteth, which in good things a man ſhall hardly ſee. A litle ſowre will ſpill a great deale of ſweete, but it is no ſmall ſtore of ſweete, that will take away but a litle bitterneſſe. A litle blacke wil marre a great deale of white: but it is not ſo in the contrarie. It is not ſo eaſie for a drop of water to quench a great fire, as it is for a litle ſparke to burne vp a whole citie. By this which hath beene alreadie ſaid, it may ſufficiently appeare how ſtrongly the euill example of wicked Princes doth induce, and draw the common people to imitate ſuch vices as they ſee in their Princes vnder whom they liue. And let this ſuffice to haue obſerued in the perſon of <hi>Ahab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the people whom the Prophet reproueth in this, for their halting conſciences, and doubling in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14083:11"/> matter of religion, we may ſee the proneneſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of mans corrupt kind and nature to the moſt abominable vice of idolatrie. True it is, that mans nature at the firſt had vnderſtanding graunted to the end that the truth might be learned by them, and the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the one God, the onely Lord and maker of all. But the diuels malice craftily came in place, and cauſed men to forget their owne eſtate, and the maieſtie of God for their owne imaginations. So that fleſh delighting in her owne deuiſes, hath made vs prone aboue all other faultes, to ſuperſtition and wicked worſhippings. Sundrie lawes and ordinances almightie God deliuered to his people to be kept: yet concerning none other matter, did he giue either mo, or more earneſt, and expreſſe lawes than thoſe that concerned the true worſhipping of him, and flying of idolles, and images and idolatrie, and yet it is ſtrange to conſider how the Iewes the onely choſen people of God, notwithſtanding they were ſo often, and earneſtly warned, ſo dreadfully threatned con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning images; ſo many times and ſo extreamely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed therefore, ſhould yet for all this, like blinde men without all knowledge and vnderſtanding diſhonour and diminiſh the high maieſtie of the liuing God by the baſeneſſe and vileneſſe of ſundrie and diuerſe images of dead ſtones, and ſtockes, and mettalles to whom they bowed and gaue worſhip.</p>
            <p>The meanes how the people of the Iewes fell to ſuch groſſe idolatrie, was partly by the inclination of their owne corrupt nature, and partly occaſioned by the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles and heathen people dwelling round about them, which were idolaters: for thus the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth of them, that they were wont to ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze.</hi> 20.32.</note> 
               <hi>we will be as the heathen, and as the families of the countries, and we will ſerue wood and ſtone.</hi> We ſee how the Iewes forced <hi>Aaaron</hi> afore his brother <hi>Moſes</hi> could deſcend from the mount, to make them a golden calfe: Vp ſay they to <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.1.</note> and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14083:12"/> 
               <hi>Aaron, make vs goddes that may goe before vs.</hi> Ezechiel affirmeth, that when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were yet in <hi>Egypt,</hi> they had rebelled againſt the Lord, and had not caſt away the abominations of their eyes, nor yet forſaken the idolles of the countrie. Yea when they were in the land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> they had no ſooner taſted of the ſweetneſſe thereof, but <hi>when they ſaw euery hie hill, and all the thicke trees, they offered there their ſacrifices,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze.</hi> 20 28.</note> 
               <hi>and there they preſented their offerings of prouocation: there alſo they made their ſweete ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and powred out there their drinke offerings.</hi> We may reade and ſee in the booke of Iudges, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding God ſundrie times moſt grieuouſly plagued them for their idolatrie; yet ſtill they went a madding after their idolles. We ſee that after the zealous kings <hi>Ezechias</hi> and <hi>Ioſias</hi> had reformed religion, and reduced it to his ancient puritie, the people were ſo prone to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that immediately the people after their deceaſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to their vomite againe. Yea when the ten tribes were brought to Captiuitie for ſeruing God otherwiſe then he would, the tribe of <hi>Iuda</hi> was not by this their brethrens plague amended: nor when they were brought vnder yoke themſelues, they conſidered any whit, the cauſe of their diſtreſſe, which was the forſaking of the Lord their God. When they were in <hi>Babylon,</hi> they went as neere as they could to the rites of gentilitie, and returning againe into the land of promiſe, vnder <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochus</hi> they fell againe. Such is, and ſuch hath alwaies been the violent perſwaſion of errour, and ſuch is the force of ſuperſtition, that aſſoone as euer occaſion is miniſtred, our corrupt nature inclineth to it, deſiring alwaies of our ſelues to attemper goddes ſeruice to our outward ſenſes. That bleſſed impe, our late <hi>Ioſias,</hi> K. <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. was no ſooner departed this life, but the common people of the land, as though they had neuer heard of God, neuer heard any Preacher that ſhewed them the good and right way, were mad after pilgrimages, pardons, &amp;c: with other
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14083:12"/> ſuch idle toyes. No maruaile then, if al men generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as wel inclined of their owne corrupt nature to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall fornication as to carnall, and that the nature of man is no otherwiſe bent to worſhipping of images (if he may haue them, and ſee them) then to whoredome and forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in the company of harlots, no meruaile I ſay, if ſo many occaſions being miniſtred partly by the Prieſts and Ieſuites remaining in priſons, and lurking in diuerſe parts of this kingdome, and partly by the comming in of forraine Embaſſadours into this land, which are in right permitted to haue the free vſe and exerciſe of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Romane Religion, there are ſo many of our people, ſpecially of women (a ſex euer too credulous and apt to beleeue) which are like the idolatrous Iewes, euen mad in running to heare and ſee a Prieſt ſay Maſſe, which Maſſe they are ſtrongly borne in hand, that it is the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious treaſure, and inualuable iewell that euer Chriſt left to his Church, that the want thereof is to be redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not onely with the loſſe of an 100 markes, but with the loſſe of an 100. thouſand liues. But to ſpeake of the Maſſe, as the truth of the thing requireth, and as hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I will more largely proue, this I ſay, that the popiſh Maſſe, as now it is vſed in the Church of Rome, is a very ſea of abominations, a gulfe, a hel of iniquitie, the vileſt villaine that euer crept into the Church of God, being ſo many waies derogatorie to the death and bloodſhedding of Ieſus Chriſt, wherein poore ſimple ſoules are forced to attribute diuine honour to a peece of breade, which the Papiſts teach them to call their Lord and their God, and alſo made beleeue that the very hearing of a Maſſe is auailable vnto them <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> that is, onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſaid and done; and laſtly, that the Maſſe in all reſpects of power and vertue is as auailable and effectuall for the remiſſion of ſinnes, as was the ſacrifice of Chriſt vpon the croſſe, the abſurditie of which poſitions ſhall receiue a iuſt confutation, when I come to lay downe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14083:13"/> ſuch arguments and proofes as may be produced out of the word of God, for the diſprouing of their daily Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of their Maſſe.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus farre ſpoken of the perſon of <hi>Elias,</hi> and of the perſon of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and of the people, whom the prophet <hi>Elias</hi> thus reproueth;<note place="margin">The thing hee reproueth.</note> it remaineth now that I ſpeake of the ſpeciall thing which hee reproueth in them: that is, their halting betweene two opinions, not being reſolued whether God were the Lord, or <hi>Baal.</hi> Which may ſeeme the more ſtrange, that this people which were the ſeede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Lords owne inheritance, the dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of Gods owne ſoule, a people whome the Lorde had choſen among all Nations, to be a precious people to himſelfe, aboue all people on the earth, in Name, praiſe, and glorie: A people that ſo many times, and ſo ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie had proteſted, <hi>God forbid wee ſhould forſake the Lord our God, to ſerue other Gods: the Lord our God we will ſerue, and his voyce wee will obey:</hi> that this people (I ſay) ſhould ſtand in doubt, whether that GOD that had wrought ſo many miracles for their deliuerance, which had brought them out of the Land of <hi>Egipt,</hi> with a ſtrong and a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hand, which had led them, and fed them in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with <hi>Manna</hi> from heauen, for the ſpace of 40. yeares, preſeruing them in all the way which they went, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying their enemies before them, &amp; laſtly in the ende, bringing them into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> whether he were the onely true God to be worſhipped and followed, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Baal,</hi> in ſo much, that when the prophet <hi>Elias</hi> had ſaid vnto them, <hi>If the Lorde be God followe him: if Baal be hee, goe after him.</hi> Silence was the onely anſwere they made him, being not able otherwiſe to anſwere him one word.</p>
            <p>Vnto this baſe irreſolution the people were thus deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately brought; partly being moued through feare of ſo great and mightie a Prince, and ſo greatly aduancing the worſhip of <hi>Baal,</hi> as king <hi>Ahab</hi> did, by the inticement
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14083:13"/> and prouocation of his wife. So that perceiuing how both the King and Queene, and almoſt all the Nobilitie, being wholly affected &amp; addicted to the worſhip of <hi>Baal,</hi> by reaſon of the weakeneſſe and infirmitie of their faith, were not able to reſolue in themſelues, what they might doe, or how they might belieue, ſtanding in a mamme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this way and that way, one and the ſame man would ſomtimes worſhip the Lord, and an other while <hi>Baal,</hi> and ſometimes both together, being perſwaded that religion was a thing indifferent, and that it did not matter how they ſerued God, if they had any care at all to ſerue him, whether they ſerued him alone, or ſerued him with anie other. But little did this people vnderſtand that religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not as euerie common matter of mans life: but a thing to be meaſured, not by opinion, but by truth; to be choſen, not by example, but by iudgement; to be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, not for companie, but for conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p>In this irreſolution and wauering inconſtancie of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> wee may as in a glaſſe, beholde and ſee our ſelues, euen the ſtate and condition of our owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; how manie there are yet in our dayes, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they haue bene bred and brought vp in this religion, which by Gods great mercy this day is profeſſed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> yet partly by the corruption of their owne nature, partly led by the mouing perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of recuſant Papiſts, but ſpecially being inticed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, by thoſe falſe impoſtors &amp; deceiuers of the world, I meane the Prieſts and Ieſuites, beginne to call the truth of our religion into queſtion, ſtanding in a maze, what they may doe, whome they may followe, what they may belieue; ſometime in loue and liking of our religion, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhile againe, being wearie of the Goſpell, imbracing the <hi>Romane</hi> religion, falſely called by the name of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi> Religion, and ſo daily wauering betweene two opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, declare themſelues indeed to bee of no Religion. For whom as my daily prayer to God is and ſhall be, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14083:14"/> he would be pleaſed to graunt them a ſolide and ſtrong perſwaſion in the profeſſion and defence of the true, and onely ancient Catholike faith of Chriſt deliuered vnto vs in the holy ſcriptures of God, and withall, ſuch a meaſure of heauenly wiſedome, that they may be able to diſcerne things that differ one from another, and to giue a ſound iudgement betweene that which is counterfaite, and the true Catholike faith and religion of Chriſt. So I could wiſh, that they would conſider with mee, and that they would ſeriouſly ponder with earneſt and vpright aduiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment theſe fewe reaſons, or motiues, which here I will ſet downe, which may ſerue in ſteed of ſo many ſeuerall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations, to proue that this ſame doctrine we preach this day in all the reformed churches of Chriſtendome, is the verie truth of the Goſpel of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, I would haue them but to weigh the beginnings and proceedings of our religion, how in a manner, all the trauels of our aduerſaries haue come to nought, and how no bodie driuing it forward without any worldlie helpe, it hath taken increaſe, and by little &amp; little is ſpread ouer into all countreys And verilie it cannot chuſe but carrie great weight of perſwaſion, to moue the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of any man, to ſee ſo many kingdoms and countries ioyne together in the profeſſion and obedience of one truth. And there is no doubt but euen this day, manie thouſandes are the ſooner led to humble themſelues to the Goſpell of Chriſt, for that they ſee (to the vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able griefe of the Pope and his fauourites) the whole world, that is to ſay, the whole Church of God is conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſo willingly and ſo humbly to imbrace the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, let them but conſider, that they haue ſeene with their owne eyes, how the Goſpell which hath bene preached vnto them, and which ſomtimes with ioy they haue receiued, euen amiddes ſo many ſtormes and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, through death and perſecution, notwithſtanding the abundance of innocent Chriſtian blood, which hath
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14083:14"/> beene ſhed ouer all the world, hath had a ſtrange and wonderfull increaſe, ſo that the more our religion hath beene perſecuted, the more ſtill it hath increaſed, and this was euer reputed by the ancient fathers, to be the proper priuiledge and excellencie of truth, about all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſects, to come out of perſecution as gold out of the fire, more bright, more illuſtrious, more eminent then before.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> A third motiue or forcible inducement to iuſtifie the truth of the Goſpel now preached, may be this, euen the due conſideration of that vniuerſalitie of learning, and ſauing knowledge, wherewith God hath bleſſed theſe daies of ours, more plentifully, and in greater meaſure then in former times he hath done. In ſo much that whereas the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaking of that aboundance of knowledge, which ſhould be vnder the kingdome of Chriſt, in the time of grace, hath theſe words,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>The earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſea: and likewiſe the Prophet</hi> Ioel,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2.28.</note> 
               <hi>I will powre out my ſpirit vpon all fleſh, and your ſonnes and your daughters ſhall prophecie: Your old men ſhall dreame dreames, and your yong men ſhall ſee viſions, and alſo vpon the ſeruants, and handmaides will I poure my ſpirit.</hi> We may truly ſay in this accepted time, and this day of ſaluation, that theſe ſcriptures are fulfilled in our eares, euen our enemies being iudges, who haue confeſſed that the word of God was neuer in any age ſo plainely taught and deliuered, as in this time wherein we liue, that we may truly and iuſtly ſay, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the words of our Sauiour Chriſt to ourſelues, bleſſed are the eyes which haue ſeene thoſe things which we haue ſeene, there hauing beene many millions and thouſands of our forefathers, which deteſting the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian pride, &amp; other looſe behauiour of the Romane Clergie, endeuouring to ſerue the Lord after the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of his owne word, deſired to haue ſeene, but one of the daies which we haue ſeene and could not: who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14083:15"/> with <hi>Lot,</hi> they vexed their righteous ſoules in the middes of a <hi>ſpirituall Sodome,</hi> yet like Sea-fiſh, which is alwaies moſt freſh in ſalt-water, they kept themſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted of the world, and would not ſpot their ſoules with ſuch horrible co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taminations, wherwith the whole world almoſt was defiled in thoſe times of great darkneſſe and ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>The concluſion is this; that ſeeing ouer all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world, where the Goſpell hath had free paſſage, all thoſe places whereſoeuer the ſound thereof is heard, are full of the knowledge of the Lord; and that on the other ſide, where poperie preuaileth, there is nothing but ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and ſuperſtition, the truth with tyrannie &amp; cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie being kept vnder, by reaſon of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that this is a verie ſtrong motiue to perſwade, that the Goſpell this day preached in the reformed Churches of Chriſtendome, is the infallible and vndoubted word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthlie, it was euer reputed and accounted for a ſpeciall fruite of the Goſpel, to teach people obedience to their Gouernours, to vpholde the State and Maieſtie of Kings and Princes, into whoſe hands God hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſword of publike authoritie. Now our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries cannot chuſe but ſee, and all the Chriſtian world can witneſſe with vs this day, that in all theſe places where at this preſent through Gods goodnes and mercy, the truth of the goſpel is taught, all ſuch places are become more obedient to ſuperior powers then euer they were before. That there is greater maieſtie to be found, leſſe arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and tyrannie: the Prince more honoured, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth and Church in far greater quiet, then in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time of corruption, when neither the Prince knewe what belonged to him, nor the ſubiects knewe what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belonged either to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or vnto God.</p>
            <p>And verilie one reaſon to perſwade anie mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that poperie is not of God, may be this: that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14083:15"/> the doctrine of the Goſpel is a doctrine of obedience, which Chriſt both taught and acted; his Apoſtles both by precept and practiſe confirmed: &amp; whereas the whole current and ſtreame of antiquitie runneth the ſame way, that all manner of perſons, yea the BB. of Rome them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for many hundred yeares together, did acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Emperour for their Lord, liege Lord and Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; the doctrine of the preſent Church of Rome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth flatly to diſobedience and plaine rebellion. It teacheth that the people vpon the Popes warrant may lawfully beare armes againſt their ſoueraigne: that by diſpenſation from the Pope, they may lawfully renounce their allegiance, yea further vpon the Popes iubet, they may lay violent hands vpon him. And ſo the Ieſuites haue deliuered it for the reſolute and vndoubted iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church of Rome, <hi>that it is a thing both lawfull, and meritorious to kill and to murther Chriſtian Princes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing a contrarie religion to the doctrine and faith of that Church,</hi> poperie therfore that profeſſeth, not a lawfulnes onely, but a merite in ſuch deſperate attempts, contrarie to the manifeſt voyce of God, Thou ſhalt not kill, doth clearely conuince it ſelfe, and ſhew it ſelfe to be a religion of the diuell, and not of God. Let this then ſuffice for a concluſion of my fourth motiue, to ſhew, that this is the alone propertie of the Goſpel, whereſoeuer true religion flouriſheth, to ſeaſon the hearts both of young and old with true ſubiection and Chriſtian obſequiouſneſſe to the higher and ſuperiour powers.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly if long peace, wealth and proſperitie to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bleſſings of God (as vndoubtedly they be) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he declareth his ſpeciall fauour vnto that Prince and kingdome, which feare him, and worſhip him ſincerely, and with whom he is well pleaſed, according to his word and promiſes in the ſcriptures, that this muſt be an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both of the ſingular fauour of god to all proteſtant Princes that haue imbraced the Goſpel, and of the ſincere
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14083:16"/> religion profeſſed by them wherewith he is well pleaſed. For of all the Kings of <hi>Iuda,</hi> who euer more abounded with all peace and worldly felicitie then thoſe who were moſt religiouſly addicted and affected to the ſeruice of God, as <hi>Ioſias, Ezechias, Iehoſaphat, Dauid, Salomon?</hi> Thus the Lord ſpake to king <hi>Iehoiaekim</hi> by his Prophet <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 22.15.</note> 
               <hi>Did not thy father</hi> Ioſias <hi>eate and drinke and proſper when he executed iudgement and iuſtice? and was not all this becauſe he knew me, ſaith the Lord?</hi> What Prince was there euer in the world either more honoured or feared then <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great was after he had once receiued the Chriſtian religion? all the kingdomes this day poſſeſſed with proteſtant Princes, all the free cities and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths of <hi>Heleutia,</hi> neuer were in more riches or ſetled tranquilitie: neuer ſo potent, nor ſo orderly gouerned as they be at this day, religion there hauing ſo free a paſſage, and courſe among them as it hath, and to come neerer home to our owne daies, if we doe but conſider with our owne ſelues the long, peaceable and proſperous raigne of our late dread ſoueraigne Queene Elizabeth, the very ioy of Chriſtendome, whoſe land in her daies, was a ſanctuarie to all the world groning for the libertie of true religion, we ſhall perceiue that from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of her moſt happie raigne vntill the day of her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, by gods ſingular goodneſſe, this kingdome of great Britaine, hath enioyed more vniuerſall peace, the people of the land encreaſed in greater numbers in more ſtrength, with greater riches, and leſſe ſickneſſe, the earth hath yeelded more fruits, and generally al kind of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly felicitie hath more abounded ſince, and during the time of the Popes thunders, bulles, curſes and male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, then in any other long time before, when the Popes pardons and bleſſings came yearely into the Realme, as they did in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> daies. And thus much for proofe that the outward bleſſings of God, which he hath beſtowed vpon ſuch Kings and Princes,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14083:16"/> and ſtates as haue embraced the Goſpel of his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus, are vndoubted arguments and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the true and ſincere religion profeſſed by them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The laſt motiue to perſwade any Chriſtian man, not wilfully blinde to embrace the religion this day profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the reformed Churches, is with an vnpartiall eye to conſider the great, ſtrange and maruelous things, which the Lord hath done for the honour and aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Goſpel in ſuch places where it hath bene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. Is it not ſtrange that <hi>Martine Luther</hi> hauing his enemies ſo many, ſo malicious, ſo mightie, ſhould not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding after nine and twentie yeares preaching, die quietly in his bed, in peace both of body and minde, and be buried with that honour, that fewe of his ranke and ſorte was euer before? Who could euer haue thought that after ſuch a ſtraunge and a moſt cruell maſſacre in France about the yeare 1572. there ſhould haue beene remaining ſo much as any one Proteſtant aliue? and yet notwithſtanding all that crueltie, though fewe in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber forſaken and deſtitute of all worldly aſſurances, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought as it were to nothing, haue yet ſtrangely and indeed miraculouſly lifted vp their heads againe to the terrour and confuſion of their proudeſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>Againe how can we conceiue it poſſible, that the citie of <hi>Geneua</hi> ſhould euer be able to hold out ſo long againſt ſo many intended inuaſions and plottes by the Duke of Sauoie entending their vtter ruine and deſolation, but that the hands of their armies were ſtrengthened by the hand of the mightie God of <hi>Iacob,</hi> their ſtrong redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, who maintaining their cauſe againſt the rage of their enemies, compaſſed them about with many ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deliuerances, hiding them as it were a ſhaft in the quiuer of his moſt carefull, and mercifull proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:14083:17"/>
            <p>What was purpoſed and intended by that inuincible Nauie of the Spaniards in 88. the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> world can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that it was nothing elſe but to bring this noble Realme of England into ſlauiſh bondage. And did not almightie God the ſonne ſtand vpon our gard by getting himſelfe honour vpon <hi>Pharao,</hi> and vpon all the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> euen vpon that great <hi>Armado,</hi> which had beene ſo long in preparing, ſo that their Altar-God, their Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix God, their Capitolian God, were not as our God, our enemies being iudges, ſundrie of the ſouldiours of <hi>Spaine</hi> confeſſing, that during all the time of the fight at ſea, Chriſt had <hi>ſhewed himſelfe a plaine Lutherane.</hi> But let vs looke a litle further into the exceeding fauour of God ſhewed in particular to the late Queene Elizabeth, how many and ſundrie times was her deareſt blood ſought, and how neere the bloudie traitours haue beene to the very execution of their diueliſh deſignements, ſome of them and more then once or twice, in neereſt and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate places with their murderous weapons in their hands, and yet behold how ſtill they were preuented, the Lord ſtriking them with ſuch a ſuddaine trembling of heart, and aſtoniſhment of minde, that they had neuer the power once to lay violent hands vpon her?</p>
            <p>If all this doe not ſuffice for proofe of the truth on our ſide, and not with the Papiſts, let goddes ſpeciall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour miraculouſly ſhewed to the Kings maieſtie that now is, and his exceeding bleſſings vpon this our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie by his moſt happie entrance vnto this crowne, and ſucceſſe to this kingdome, be to vs as it is indeed, an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that the religion profeſſed this day, is the true religion acceptable to God, &amp; conformable to his word: but as God in all ages hath ſhewed his power in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous and gracious deliuerance of his Church, and protection of his holie and eternall truth, ſo did it neuer more cleerely ſhewe it ſelfe, then in the wonderfull and mighty deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our gracious K. <hi>Iames,</hi> the Queene,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14083:17"/> the Prince, and the reſt of the royall braunches, together with the Nobilitie, Clergie, and the Commons of this Realme, by the pouder-Traytors, the papiſts, appointed as ſheepe for the ſlaughter. And let thus much be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to haue ſpoken touching the ſtrange and wonderful things which <hi>almighty God</hi> hath ſhewed in theſe laſt daies, for the honour of his Goſpell, for the better ſatisfaction of them which as yet ſtand in doubt, whether the Goſpel we preach, be the onely true &amp; Catholike faith of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But beſides thoſe men which ſtand at a ſtay, and are not yet reſolued, which religion, I meane ours or the papiſts is trueſt, ther is riſen another generation of men, that are of opinion, that there is no reall difference between the doctrine of the preſent <hi>Romane</hi> church, &amp; the religion of the proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; ſo make a fauorable compromiſſion, that the queſtions of religion betweene vs might eaſily be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, which I take to be a thing altogether impoſſible, the Papiſts ſtanding in ſuch termes of oppoſition againſt vs as they doe. I remember my ſelfe preaching at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine countrey pariſh, ſome three yeeres agoe, a ſimple countrey man commeth vnto me, and thus beginneth to queſtion with me: Syr, your preachers make vs ſimple men of the countrey belieue, that there is a wonderfull great difference betweene the new &amp; old Religion. Pray Sir, ſaith he, what oddes is there betweene <hi>Our Father,</hi> and <hi>Pater noſter?</hi> None at all, ſaid I, but onely this, that the one is in Latine, and the other in Engliſh. You haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered right (ſaith he, and ſo I am perſwaded) that there is no other difference at all betweene the Maſſe &amp; our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Communion, but onely that the one is in Latin, the other in Engliſh. And of this opinion it ſeemeth ther be manie, which thinke and are perſwaded, that our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the religion of <hi>Rome,</hi> are all one for ſubſtance. For ſatisfaction therefore of them which thinke our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Communion and the popiſh Maſſe all one for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, I will ſet downe certaine reall differences, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14083:18"/> it may euidently appeare, that the doctrine of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Maſſe, neither hath, nor can haue any agreeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at all with the Lordes ſupper. I ſpeake at this time to men of great vnderſtanding &amp; knowledge, iudge yee what I ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, whereas all the ſeruice and ſacraments in <hi>S. Pauls</hi> time, were done in the congregation, in a knowne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, the whole ſeruice of the Maſſe is ſaide either in the Greeke or Latine tongues, not vnderſtood of the common vulgar people.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Chriſt both gaue bread, and likewiſe commanded them ſaying, <hi>Drinke yee all of this;</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will at no hand ſuffer and permit the Lay-people to drinke of the Cup, calling them <hi>Heretikes,</hi> and <hi>Calixtions,</hi> that deſire to receiue the Cup together with the bread, in the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> By Chriſts inſtitution the Prieſt and the people ſhould both communicate together: but in their Popiſh Maſſe the Prieſt is ſuffered to eate and drinke all alone, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtanding by, and not partaking the Lords ſupper with him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Chriſt at his <hi>Maundie</hi> inſtituted a Sacrament of thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, and commaunded vs by eating and drinking to be partakers of his bodie that was wounded, and of his blood which was ſhed the next day, for the remitting and pardoning of our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath turned this Sacrament into a Sacrifice. And whereas the Sonne of God ſaide, <hi>Take this and eate it in remembrance of mee,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſaith, take and offer this to bee a propitiatorie ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the quicke and the dead.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Chriſt tooke the bread in his hands, bleſſed it, and gaue it to his Diſciples: but hee did not ſay, looke vpon it, kneele, and knock vnto it, and worſhip it with diuine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, all which the church of <hi>Rome</hi> commandeth to be done in their popiſh Maſſe: but as Chriſt took the bread, ſo he left it bread, whereas the popiſh Prieſt takes bread,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14083:18"/> and coniureth it away, by breathing vpon it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Laſtly, Chriſt ordained his laſt Supper, and inſtituted this Sacrament of his bodie and bloud, to this ende, that we ſhould continually remember his death vntill his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond comming, and for that cauſe it is called <hi>Euchariſtia.</hi> And whereas <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith, that Chriſt commaunded vs to offer vp a remembrance of his death in ſteed of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, the popiſh church not conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting themſelues with this ſacrifice of praiſe, and thankſgiuing, wherein we cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the remembrance, and as <hi>Nazianzene</hi> calleth it, <hi>A figure of that great myſterie of the death of Christ,</hi> they hold that their Maſſe, which they call <hi>The daily Sacrifice of the Church,</hi> is not a commemoratiue, but a reall ſacrifice, not a figure and remembrance of that which is paſt, but the thing it ſelfe: that the ſacrifice Chriſt offered vpon the Croſſe, and theirs in the Maſſe is all one: that the ſame bodie of Chriſt which was borne of the Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> and which was offered vp, vpon the Croſſe for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, is the very ſame, euen <hi>idem numero,</hi> with that which is offered vp by the Prieſt, to God the Father in the Maſſe, for the remiſſion of ſinnes. By theſe materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all differences, which here I haue ſet downe, it is plainely manifeſt, that the popiſh Maſſe doth in manie things va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie &amp; ſwarue from the inſtitution of Chriſt, as moſt plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is to be ſeene, in the 11. cha: of 1. <hi>Corint: verſ.</hi> 23. where the Apoſtle at large doth deſcribe the whole order and inſtitution of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>And thus it is euidently to be perceiued, that the Maſſe as now it is vſed, is nothing elſe, but an heape of ſinfull deuiſes, and abuſes, inuented by Sathan and broached by Antichriſt, to deface &amp; fruſtrate the Lords ſupper: where beſides their fruiteleſſe praiers, and ſuperſtitious ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, their priuate and halfe communion ſubuerteth the Lordes inſtitution: their ſacrifice derogateth from his death and bloud-ſheading: their adoration of bread and wine, conuinceth them of hainous Idolatrie.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:14083:19"/>
            <p>But to proue that Proteſtancy and poperie cannot be reconciled: Firſt, the Papiſts themſelues bold the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences betweene vs to bee ſuch: that it is impoſſible for any Proteſtant to be ſaued.</p>
            <p>Againe, all the grounded diuines of the Proteſtants re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion inſiſt vpon the ſame differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. That ſundry points of poperie doe quite raze the verie foundation of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion. Marke (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Iewell</hi> to D. <hi>Harding) What yee were lately, and what yee would now ſeeme to bee: what way yee trode then, and what way yee treade now: the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is no leſſe then betweene light and darkeneſſe; life and death; heauen and hell:</hi> ſo great a change (ſaith hee) would require ſome good time of deliberation. Which aſſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of that worthy Biſhop, how agreeable it is to the truth, and conſonant to the practiſe of the ancient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike church, and Doctors thereof, who would neuer yeeld, I will not ſay in an opinion, but not ſo much as in a forme of ſpeech, or in the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of a letter, ſounding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>orthodoxall</hi> faith: and whether there bee not in ſundry fundamentall points of faith, great and many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences betweene <hi>Rome</hi> and vs, let it be duely conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by theſe inſtances following.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt maine point of Catholike doctrine, which the Papiſts goe directly againſt, is the doctrine of <hi>free iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by faith alone,</hi> which doctrine D. Biſhop in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle dedicatory to the K. Maieſtie, ſetteth down as a maine hereſie, that <hi>Luther</hi> layed for the ground of his religion: namely, <hi>that a man is iustified by faith alone.</hi> But I demaund of any ſober Papiſt, not too much wedded to the preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of his own opinion, what other, or what better foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation could any man lay, then that which is already laid, which is Ieſus Chriſt, which doctrine is the very life and ſoule of the Church.</p>
            <p>For this was the Catholike faith of the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when <hi>S. Paule</hi> wrote his Epiſtle vnto them, <hi>that a man is iuſtified gratis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24.</note> 
               <hi>for God a mercie, for nothing, and that by the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14083:19"/> grace of God without the workes of the law.</hi> Quite contrarie to which doctrine of the Apoſtle, the Papiſts hold iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by workes of grace, auouching that we are not iuſtified before God, onely by the merites of Chriſt, but alſo by our owne doings, affirming that good workes are truely and properly meritorious, and the cauſes of our ſaluation, and that heauen is as truely the reward of good workes, as hell is the ſtipend of euill workes: that good workes doe fully ſatisfie the law of God, and worthily deſerue eternall life: and that good workes wrought and done in the ſtate of grace, are ſo farre meritorious, as that God ſhould be vniuſt, if he rendred not heauen for the ſame, charging the iuſtice of God, not in reſpect of his promiſe, as the Apoſtle doth, but in reſpect of merite, and deſert of workes. Where we clearely perceiue and ſee, that there is a great difference betweene the Church of Rome and vs, euen in the principall Article of our faith touching the Saluation of our ſoules; we beleeuing ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly, that it is to be aſcribed to the merites of Chriſt, they expecting it for the merit of their workes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Another ſubſtantiall point of the Catholike faith the Papiſts directly impugne, in maintaining a daily reall ſacrifice of the body of Chriſt in their Maſſe for the ſins of the quicke and dead, which they hold to be a very ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, true, and propitiatorie ſacrifice, &amp; in all reſpects of power and vertue, as auailable, and as effectuall as was the ſacrifice on the croſſe for the remiſſion of ſinnes. For the diſproofe of which moſt wicked and blaſphemous aſſertion, there be ſundrie arguments and proofes to be produced out of the word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt if Chriſt could haue bene offered more then once, then muſt he likewiſe after haue ſuffered. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.25.26.</p>
            <p>But now in the end of the world he hath appeared once to put away ſinne by the ſacrifice of himſelfe. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26.</p>
            <p>Therefore he cannot now any more be offered in the Maſſe.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:14083:20"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, that thing is in vaine and to none effect, where there is no neceſſitie it ſhould be done: but to offer vp any more ſacrifice propitiatorie for the quicke and the dead, there is no neceſſitie: the reaſon whereof the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle giueth to be this, becauſe Chriſt hath offered one ſacrifice, and with that one ſacrifice, and offering vp of himſelfe, hath conſecrated for euer them that are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10 12.14.</p>
            <p>This muſt then be the concluſion, that there is no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie why we ſhould offer vp Chriſt any more for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the reaſon why the Prieſts of the old law did yearely repeate their ſacrifices was this, becauſe thoſe ſacrifices yearely offered, could neuer take away ſinnes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.11. But the ſacrifice of Chriſt once offered hath ſanctified the commers thereunto: for wee are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied euen by the offering of the bodie of Ieſus Chriſt once made, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.10.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſeeing that Chriſt by that one oblation of himſelfe hath purchaſed for vs eternall redemption, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12. there needeth no more propitiatorie ſacrifice to be made for ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Where there is remiſſion of ſinnes alreadie obtained, there is no more offering for ſinne, there needeth no more ſacrifice to be offered, <hi>Heb.</hi> 14.18. But Chriſt hath beene offered once to take away the ſinnes of many, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28. and by his owne blood he hath entred once to the holy place to obtaine eternal rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption for vs: <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Maſſe cannot be a propitiatorie ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for ſinnes, ſeeing alreadie by the death of Chriſt we haue remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſtly, without blood and ſhedding of blood, there is no forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22.</p>
            <p>But in the daily ſacrifice of the Maſſe there is no ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of blood, for they call their Maſſe an vnbloodie ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:14083:20"/>
            <p>Therefore in the ſacrifice of the Maſſe there is no remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes, and ſo by conſequent the Maſſe can be no true propitiatorie ſacrifice. Thus we ſee how the doctrine of the popiſh Maſſe is <hi>ex diametro</hi> repugnant to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Apoſtle, and to the whole order and inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> A third very materiall and ſubſtantiall point of the Chriſtian Catholike faith impugned this day by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Romane Church, is this, that contrarie to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words of our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him onely thou ſhalt ſerue:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 4.10.</note> contrarie to the commandement which the Angel gaue to <hi>Iohn,</hi> when he fell at his feete to worſhip him: <hi>See thou doe it not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reue.</hi> 19.10.</note> 
               <hi>I am thy fellow ſeruant, and of thy bretheren which haue the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Ieſus, worſhip God: contrarie to the examples of</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Barnabas,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 14.15.</note> Which vtterly refuſed all manner of adoration, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> renting their clothes cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out to the people of Lycaonia, <hi>O men why doe ye theſe things? We are euen men ſubiect to the like paſſions, ye be,</hi> and preach vnto you <hi>that ye ſhould turne from theſe vaine idolles vnto the liuing God, which made heauen and earth, and the ſea, and all things that in them are:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10.25.</note> and <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> (Who at his firſt meeting of him <hi>fell downe at his feete and worſhipped him</hi>) ſaid thus vnto him, taking him vp, <hi>ſtand vp: for euen I my ſelfe am a man,</hi> contrarie to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall and conſtant practiſe of the ancient Catholike primitiue Church of Chriſt, which as S. <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> witneſſeth, did neither worſhip Sunne nor Moone, nor Angell, nor Archangell, nor Cherubin, nor Seraphin, nor any other name, that is named either in this world, or in the world to come, leaſt they ſhould ſerue the creature in ſteed of the creator, who is God bleſſed for euer: contrarie to the determination of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great and firſt of that name, who alſo himſelfe was Biſhop of Rome, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his voice to be accounted as an oracle of God, who albeit hee did well like the hauing of images in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14083:21"/> Church, yet he vtterly condemneth the idolatrous wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of them alleaging for proofe thereof the place of ſcripture before named,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>7.</hi> epiſto. cap. <hi>109.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this I ſay notwithſtanding the Church of Rome this day, euen in this cleare light of the Goſpel main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and defends the worſhip and adoration of Angels: the worſhip of Saints departed: the worſhip of the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the trinitie: the worſhip of the croſſe and crucifixe: the worſhip of images which they ſet vp in their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to the intent the people may attribute diuine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour vnto them, and laſtly the worſhip of their breaden-God, their ſacrament of the Altar, as they terme it, whom they call their Lord and their God, crying out to a peece of bread, <hi>O Lord, O God, O Lambe of God that takeſt away the ſins of the world, haue mercie vpon vs,</hi> and receiue our praiers.</p>
            <p>And verily were there no other cauſe to induce all good Chriſtians to depart from the fellowſhip and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church of Rome, this one doctrine of adoration, wherein they teach the common people to call the ſacrament their Lord and God, and ſo by giuing the honour of God to a creature that is no God, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit groſſe and manifeſt Idolatrie, this point alone were cauſe ſufficient for them to deteſt both them and their religion for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 2.27.</note>For what oddes I beſeech you is there betweene thoſe blind Iewes, <hi>which ſaid to a ſtocke, thou art my father,</hi> &amp; to a <hi>ſtone thou haſt begotten me,</hi> and thoſe wilfull and blind Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts which cry vpon the Sacrament of the Altar, in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance a baſe and corruptible creature, <hi>Lord I am not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, Lord be mercifull to me a ſinner: O Lord, O God, O Lambe of God receiue our praiers.</hi> The one ſort the H. Ghoſt hath traduced for a memorable, and deteſtable crew of idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and ſo may we by the like reaſon, and vpon as good ground and warrant condemne all the Papiſts liuing this day for moſt vile and ſhameful idolaters, for adoring and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14083:21"/> worſhipping a peece of bread. O moſt horrible idolatrie!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tully</hi> himſelfe being an heathen man could ſay, <hi>Who was euer ſo very a foole,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De natu. deorum.</note> 
               <hi>as to beleeue the thing he eateth to be his God?</hi> The very children in Grammer Schoole can tell vs, that the heathens that adored <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Ceres,</hi> which firſt found out, and taught the vſe of breade and wine, whereas before they had fed on achornes, and dranke water: yet notwithſtanding they were neuer ſo fooliſh, or ſo beſotted as to giue godly honour to bread and wine.</p>
            <p>By this then, which hath bene alreadie ſpoken, it is clearely proued, that there is no compatibilitie betweene Proteſtancie &amp; Poperie, and that the diuerſitie betweene vs, is of ſo materiall and needfull points, that if they be right, wee are wrong: if wee be right, they are wrong: both they and wee cannot be both together Catholike members of the true Church.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why wee cannot account Papiſts for mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the true Church, is, becauſe they maintain ſundry points which go directly againſt the Chriſtian faith, they doe not content themſelues onely with Chriſt, nor with his Sacraments, but ſet vp other mediatours in heauen, other doctrines and ſacraments on earth. Beſides that, as I haue alreadie proued, they adore the creatures of bread and wine, in ſteede of Chriſt. They bow their knees to painted &amp; carued images: they ioyne nature with grace: mans merites with Gods mercies: vnwritten verities with holie ſcriptures: their owne ſatisfactions with the blood of Chriſt, and ſo directly impugne ſundrie fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall points of the Chriſtian faith, which generally other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they will ſeeme to hold.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect: </seg>
               </label> But I heare ſome man ſaying vnto mee, if the caſe be ſuch, the differences ſo great betweene the religion of the Papiſts and our religion, how is it poſſible that any Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant papiſt now liuing can be ſaued?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut: </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, that as in the rebellion which <hi>Abſolom</hi> made
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14083:22"/> againſt his Father <hi>Dauid,</hi> there were manie true ſubiects of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that went after <hi>Abſolon,</hi> to take his part <hi>in their ſimplicity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam:</hi> 15.11.</note> as the ſcripture recordeth, <hi>knowing nothing,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto the trecherous plottes of <hi>Abſolon</hi> did tende. So no doubt charitie moueth mee to thinke that there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in this Kingdome, honeſt men, blinded with ſome opinions of poperie, as in the queſtions of the real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, or in the number of 7. Sacraments, or in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Auricular confeſſion, or ſome ſuch ſchoole que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, not knowing or belieuing all pointes of poperie, which indeed is the very myſterie of iniquitie. Of ſuch I ſay, that <hi>in the ſimplicitie of their harts,</hi> thinke of the Popes doctrine, no otherwiſe then <hi>Dauids</hi> ſubiects did of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of <hi>Abſolon;</hi> I will not diſpaire, but verily hope that ſuch may be ſaued, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding their miſperſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in ſome points of religion, which doe not deſtroy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny article of faith, and Chriſtian beliefe.</p>
            <p>But as for the reſt of our wilfull recuſant papiſts, which both erre in the foundation, &amp; hate the truth of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell reuealed vnto them, which hate inſtruction, and ſtop their eares againſt the word, we offer vnto them, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the infallibilitie of the Popes iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalitie of his juriſdiction and power, to diſpoſe of the Kingdomes of the world, which belieue free will to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, and to do the actions of vertue without aſſiſtance of ſpeciall grace: which holde and maintaine perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of inherent righteouſneſſe, ſatisfactions, merites of condignitie, propitiatorie ſacrifice of the Maſſe: which giue Gods honour to images, maintaine iuſtification by works, and ſuch like, of ſuch I ſay, I may without breach of charitie affirme, that if they ſo liue, and ſo die, in the armes of the whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> they can neuer be ſaued.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect: </seg>
               </label> But the Papiſts replie vpon vs, and further obiect, that if the caſe of recuſant papiſts be ſuch, why then (ſay they) we muſt likewiſe condemne all our forefathers to the pit of hell, who helde none other but the ſame opinions
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14083:22"/> wee holde this day.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut: </seg>
               </label> Touching our forefathers, we both ſpeake and thinke of them, as charitie leadeth vs to thinke: we take not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs to know either the faith or repentance of them, that died before our time, and therefore we commit their iudgement vnto God. We ſay with the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.19</note> 
               <hi>The foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of God ſtandeth firme and ſure, hauing this ſeale, The Lorde knoweth who are his:</hi> and according to the ſcriptures thus wee belieue of them all, that ſuch as helde the onely foundation which is Chriſt Ieſus, in a true &amp; liuely faith, were all ſaued, although they built vpon this foundation, chaffe, ſtraw, or wood: and doubt not therefore,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.15</note> but that manie thouſands of our anceſtours, euen in thoſe times of great blindeneſſe and corruption, holding onely the ſame foundation Ieſus Chriſt were ſaued, and ſo died the ſeruants of God: notwithſtanding they were miſled and carried away with ſundrie errours and ſuperſtitions, for want of due knowledge of the word of God, which their paſtors and leaders ſhould haue inſtructed them withall.</p>
            <p>But for a further anſwere to this obiection, I ſay, that the caſe of our recuſant Papiſts liuing at this day, and the caſe of our fore-fathers, liuing in times of great corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are not peers, nor nothing like at all.</p>
            <p>The diſpariſon is this: our fore-fathers liued in a time of great blindnes, wherein there was a generall decay of learning, wherin all good liberall Arts and learning were aboliſhed. The skie growing euen darke with the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie fogges of ignorance, when their paſtours and leaders were not onely <hi>Sir Iohn lacke Latines,</hi> but <hi>S. Iohn lacke ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſties,</hi> who could neither ſpeake Latin, nor reade Engliſh, nor vnderſtand the articles of our faith, nor any part of the ſcriptures, clowdes without raine, lanthorns without light, ſalt without ſauour, blinde guides, dumbe dogges, that (as one ſaith) ſeeme to haue their ſoules giuen them in ſteede of ſalt to keepe them from ſtinking; and what maruell then, if the people being ledde by ſuch blinde
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14083:23"/> guides, became blinde themſelues, and fell into ſundrie errours? But as for our recuſant papiſts, they liue in the learnedſt age that euer was, ſince the time of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, when as the word of God and knowledge of ſauing truth, was neuer ſo plentifull and flouriſhing as now it is.</p>
            <p>Againe, the errours of our fore-fathers proceeded of meere ſimplicitie and want of iudgement.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>I.</hi> de bap. cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> Of whome I may ſay the ſame that <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſaide of <hi>Cyprian</hi> and his colleagues, erring in the doctrine of Rebaptization; That if they had bene in his time, when vpon exact and full diſcuſſion of things, it was reſolued otherwiſe, they would haue bene of an other minde: So verilie, if our fore-fathers, whoſe zeale was exceeding great, and a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious care to ſerue God, had liued in theſe latter times, and had ſeene the true groundes of our religion, they would moſt willingly haue embraced the ſame truth we profeſſe this day: many thouſands of them in their life time, deſiring to haue ſeene &amp; heard thoſe things which wee to our vnſpeakable comfort haue both heard and ſeene. And howſoeuer manie of our fore-fathers were in ſome points deceiued, yet it is manifeſtly to be proued that the worthieſt and beſt learned men in former times thought no otherwiſe then wee doe in all ſubſtantiall pointes of Chriſtan beliefe, complaining euen as we doe of the intolerable burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which the Popes laid on them in thoſe dayes, wiſhing the remouing of ſuch things as wee haue remoued.</p>
            <p>But as touching the errours of our obſtinate and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full recuſant Pap: they proceed of meere obſtinacie, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinaciouſly defending moſt dangerous errours, <hi>Hee that is deceiued,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypri. ad Iuba.</note> 
               <hi>and erreth of ſimplicitie may be pardoned: but after the truth is once reuealed, who ſo neuertheleſſe continueth in his former errours wittingly and willingly, ſinneth without pardon of ignominy, as being ouer borne by preſumption and wilfulneſſe.</hi> And this I take to be the very caſe of all our recuſant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts this day. So great an oddes there is betweene ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14083:23"/> errour and wilfull defence. Verily for my part I am perſwaded, that there is neuer a ſober and learned papiſt in this land, that can denie (if he will truly ſay, and as he thinketh in his owne conſcience) but that we are come as neere, as poſſible we could to the Church of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and Catholike Biſhops, which Church was ſound and perfit, and ſpotted with no kind of idolatrie, and haue directed according to their cuſtomes and ordinances, not onely the doctrine this day profeſſed in the Church of England, but alſo the ſacraments, and forme of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon praiers, and diuine ſeruice eſtabliſhed here among vs: the pſalmes we ſing, are <hi>Dauids:</hi> the bookes we reade are canonicall: the prayers we make are conſonant to the rule and proportion of faith, and true godlineſſe. And ſo it appeareth, that our whole leiturgie with great iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and reaſonable moderation, was purpoſely ſo fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, out of the grounds of religion, wherein both ſides doe agree, that the papiſt himſelfe might reſort vnto it, without any ſcruple or ſcandall, if faction more then rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon did not preuaile.</p>
            <p>A third difference betweene our forefathers, and our Romiſh recuſants is this: our forefathers neuer for their part euer vnderſtood the myſterie of popiſh ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, but in ſingleneſſe of their hearts embraced the generall doctrine of the Goſpel, concerning ſaluation by faith in Chriſt: thoſe damnable and treaſonable po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions which the Church of Rome propoſeth to be holden, as verities of the Catholike faith, were neuer knowne in the daies of our forefathers, that is, theſe fundamentall points of popiſh religion, viz:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that the Pope is gods vicegerent here on earth, and therefore ſuperiour to the King of England.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That it is the Popes power to depoſe the King of England, and depriue him of his crowne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> That the Pope may abſolue his ſubiects from their oath of allegiance to him.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:14083:24"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> That at the Popes commandement, the people are to take armes againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> That it is both lawfull and meritorious before God, to kill, and to murther any Chriſtian Prince, if he fall into tyrannie or misbeliefe.</p>
            <p>The ſecrets of this occupation were neuer ſo much as heard of in thoſe daies, I meane this king-killing, and Queene-killing Doctrine of the papiſts, for proofe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I will alleadge vnto you one famous and memorable example as I find it recorded.</p>
            <p>In the wofull warres with the Barons, when King <hi>Iohn</hi> was viewing of the Caſtell of Rocheſt held againſt him by the Earle of <hi>Arundel,</hi> he was eſpied by a very good Arcubalaſter, who told the Earle thereof, and ſaid that he would ſoone diſpatch that cruell tyrant, if he would but ſay the word. God forbid, <hi>vile varlet (quoth the Earle) That we ſhould proue the death of the holy one of God.</hi> What ſaid the Souldiour, ſwearing a monſtrous oath, he would not ſpare you, my Lord, if he had you at the like aduantage? <hi>No matter for that quoth the Earle, Gods good will be done, and he will diſpoſe thereof, and not the king:</hi> an anſwere fitting and beſeeming that moſt noble Earle far contrarie to the practiſe of our powder-Traitors, and likewiſe contrarie to the practiſe of the late popes of Rome, who haue beene ſo farre off from ſauing, and ſparing the life of Chriſtian Kings and Princes, that as Pope Hildebrand gaue the firſt preſident, they haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Aſſacinours to murther them, &amp; to lay violent hands vpon them, as it is plainely to be proued by the practiſe of <hi>Pius quintus, Gregory</hi> the thirtee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th, <hi>Sixtus quintus,</hi> who not onely reſolued that parricide of Princes was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but promiſed both earthly and heauenly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence to ſuch as would offer their ſeruice to kill and murther them. The truth whereof is clearely to be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the letters of <hi>Cardinal Como</hi> written to <hi>William Parrie,</hi> wherein contrarie to the manifeſt voice of God
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14083:24"/> himſelfe, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> he encourageth him to the ſlaughter of his liege Ladie and Miſtriſſe, as to an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and holy exploite.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The laſt difference and oddes which I obſerue betweene our forefathers, &amp; our Romiſh recuſants is this, that they, as they were generally forward and very zealous in that religion which they profeſſed, ſo were they as carefull to ſeeke all the good meanes they could to come to the knowledge of the truth: they faſted often: they praied much, they were moſt diligent reſorters to the houſe of prayer, knowing that it was the place that God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had made choiſe of to haue his name called on: they would reade all ſuch good bookes as poſſible they could come by, for their better inſtruction in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God: and as it is recorded, and ſtoried of many of them they would ſit vp all night in reading and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, not caring for any expenſes or charges, ſo they might attaine to come by ſuch bookes in engliſh as they deſcried: they would not ſticke ſome of them to giue fiue markes for a Bible to reade in, and many of them moſt willingly would giue a loade of haie for ſome few Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> or Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in Engliſh. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee conceiue this good hope of them, euen of all ſuch, who ſought ſo carefully to vſe al the good meanes; whereby they might attaine to the ſauing knowledge of truth, although deceiued in ſome points, yet that they had mercy ſhewed vnto them, and doe reſt in peace with God, and that the ſame God, who gaue them ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of knowledge, and would require of them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which they had, and not according to that, which they had not, did receiue them into the number of his bleſſed and elect. But the caſe of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants is a cleane other caſe. They refuſe almoſt al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of conference with learned men: they will not, nor in deed dare, onely for the feare of diſpleaſing the Popes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14083:25"/> holineſſe, reſort to our Churches, as for 11. yeares to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in the raigne of the late Queene of moſt precious and worthie memorie, all the papiſts of this kingdome did, and that without any ſcruple of conſcience, vntill they had receiued a countermand from the Biſhop of Rome, commanding them vpon paine of the blacke curſe to come no more to the Church: they are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to reade the Scriptures: the Biſhops in Queene <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> daies, cauſed it not onely to be accounted hereſie, but to be proclaimed fellonie for any lay man to haue an Engliſh Bible in his houſe, for his priuate ſolace and comfort: the learned treatiſes written by our men, they permit not their Diſciples once to reade, but interdict them euen to many of their Seminarie Prieſts; no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile then if taking this courſe, the Ieſuites and Prieſts keepe their lay followers in a perpetuall ignorance of true religion, hauing once framed them to this princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that it is a deadly ſinne, either to reade the bookes of the Proteſtants, or to heare their ſermons, or to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at their ſeruice, or to communicate with them in any religious dutie whatſoeuer. And let thus much be ſpoken touching the Prophets reprouing of the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> for wauering and halting betweene two opinions: It followeth in the next part to make proofe vnto you, that God and <hi>Baal</hi> cannot both be ioyned together in one ſeruice.</p>
            <p>There is a ſpeech of Socrates greatly commended by S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De conſen. Euang. Li. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vnumquemque deum ſic coli oportere, quomodo ſeipſum colend m praeceperat.</hi> That is, euery God was to be honoured, as <hi>u</hi> he himſelfe had giuen in commandement. Vpon which principle the ancient Romanes in the time of <hi>Tiberius</hi> the Emperour grounding themſelues, albeit they did admit the religion of all other gods, yet by no meanes they could be induced to receiue the religion of the God of the Hebrewse. The reaſon was this, they ſaw it neceſſarie that either all their idolls muſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14083:25"/> be excluded, and onely the true worſhip of God entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: or hee onely not admitted, the reſt to be honored. For by the word of God they found they could not agree together, and contrarie to his word they would not ſeeke to ſerue him, and therefore choſe rather to bee without Chriſt altogether, then to worſhip him and others with him againſt his will and commaundement. And verilie God will take it in better part that thou deuote thy ſelfe to any religion, be it neuer ſo bad, then to make a hodge podge of religion, and ſo to haue a mixture of good and bad religion together, inſomuch that I am perſwaded that the worſhip of <hi>Mahomet</hi> leſſe offendeth God, then when ſuch as are by profeſſion Chriſtians, ſhall giue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine honour to a piece of bread.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze.</hi> 20.39.</note> 
               <hi>As for you ô houſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> (ſaith God by the Prophet Ezechiel) <hi>goe you and ſerue euery one his Idol, ſeeing you will not obey me, &amp; pollute my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie altar no more with your giftes, and with your Idolls.</hi> Where the Prophet intimateth, that God had rather that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhould <hi>bee profeſſed Idolaters,</hi> then to pretend his holie name with ſuch corruptions. True religion will admit no mixture, but is ſimple. God himſelfe ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not let thy cattell gender with diuers kindes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leui:</hi> 19.19.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſowe thy fielde with mingled ſeede: neither ſhall a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of diuers colours come vpon thee:</hi> ſignifying that wee muſt ſticke to one religion, which indeed requireth the whole man, and cannot endure any doubling in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, nor any blending of <hi>Iudaiſme,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme</hi> together: nor any reconciliation at all betweene Chriſt and <hi>Belial:</hi> betweene the table of the Lorde, and the table of diuels: betweene God and <hi>Melchom:</hi> It is not poſſible that one wombe ſhould containe <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau:</hi> one houſe the Arke and <hi>Dagon:</hi> one temple pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and merchandiſe: one heauen <hi>Michaell</hi> and the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, and ſo God hauing ordained his Law ſtricktly to be kept without declining either to the right hand or to the left, giueth vs to vnderſtand, that hee himſelfe will be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14083:26"/> alone, without corriualles of his glorie, with all our heart, ſtrength, and ſoule. <hi>Sonne</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>giue mee thine heart:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro:</hi> 23.26.</note> 
               <hi>and let thine eyes delight in my wayes:</hi> but Sathan wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to part ſtakes with God, crieth out with the Harlot, <hi>Nec mihi, nec tibi, ſed diuidatur:</hi> Let honour and glorie, and worſhip bee neither mine nor thine,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King:</hi> 3.</note> but let it be diuided. But the Lorde our God beeing a iealous God, will not be crowded in a corner of the heart, but he will haue either all thine heart, or no part at all, either all glorie, or no glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: <hi>aut Caeſar, aut nullus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo we are taught by the word of God in Deutero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 61.4.5</note> 
               <hi>Heare ô Iſrael, the Lord our God is Lord only; &amp; thou ſhalt lette the Lorde thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoule, and with all thy might,</hi> that is: we muſt loue God ſweetely, ſtrongly, perſeuerantly.</p>
            <p>Loue God with all thine heart, that is, kindely and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionately. Loue God with all thy ſoule, that is, wiſely and diſcreetly. Loue God with all thy might, that is, ſtedfaſtly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly; Let the loue of thine heart inflame thy zeale to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him: Let the knowledge of thy ſoule guide it with diſcretion: Let the conſtancie of thy might and ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth confirme it: That is, let thy loue bee feruent, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and inuincible. So that thou maieſt ſay with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>I am perſwaded, that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro:</hi> 8.38.</note> 
               <hi>nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, ſhall bee able to ſeperate mee from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus my Lorde.</hi> Out of that which hath bene already ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken touching this point of mingling Gods worſhip with the worſhip of any other, this concluſion or corollarie may be deriued, which is this, that if either thou ſerue God with my other, as Saints, Angels, or anie creature, which the Papiſts doe.</p>
            <p>Or if thou ſerue him alone, any other way, then he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth, thou loueſt him not, but thou doeſt hate him, yea, extreamely hate him, and ſhalt finde at his hands the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14083:26"/> reward of a deadly enemie. Strange therefore muſt needs ſeeme to bee this Doctrine of the Papiſts, wherein they teach, that wee may honour God, as wee our ſelues can beſt deuiſe.</p>
            <p>That if our intent be good, and our meaning be good, it skilleth not how, or in what manner wee worſhip him: That theſe kindes of worſhippings of God, which come of our owne heads, without the expreſſe commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, are the more agreeable vnto him, the more they proceede of our ſelues. Which doctrine of theirs is the maine proppe of all idolatrie, and the very roote of all ſuperſtition. For the wayes of God are not as our waies: his thoughts are not as our thoughts: hee hath bridled our deuotion, and hath taught vs to worſhip him not in ſuch ſort as may ſeeme good in our eyes, but onely as hee hath commanded vs. God commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to build the tabernacle, according to that order and forme ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in the mount, neither durſt <hi>Moſes</hi> adde or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh any thing, or to doe more or leſſe, then God appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him. Certaine it is, that our good meanings make not our doings good. Neither is our zeale a rule where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee may meaſure out either our Faith, or our good workes, but onely the knowne will and pleaſure of God.</p>
            <p>There wanted no good intent, or good meaning either in the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when they made a golden calfe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod:</hi> 3.2.4</note> or in <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Al thu,</hi> when they offered ſtrange fire: or in <hi>Saul,</hi> when he ſpared king <hi>Agag:</hi> or in <hi>Vzza,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit:</hi> 10.2. 1. <hi>Sam:</hi> 15.22. 2. <hi>Sam:</hi> 6.6. 1. <hi>King:</hi> 12.28.</note> when he put his hand to the Arke to holde it: nor in <hi>Ishu,</hi> when hee would needs ioyne the worſhipping of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> golden Calues, with the worſhip of the true God of <hi>Iſraell:</hi> and yet we ſee how that iealous God which could neuer abide to be worſhipped otherwiſe then hee himſelfe had giuen in commandement, executed his fierce wrath vpon them all, for their confected religions, and halting conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces.</p>
            <p>And this for all the world, is the very guiſe and manner of worſhip the papiſts vſe: True it is, they worſhip God,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14083:27"/> and they worſhip Chriſt, but not according to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript, but in ioyning the worſhip of other creatures with the worſhip of the only true God, they proue themſelues to be plaine Idolaters, holding this for a moſt certaine doctrine, <hi>that the Crucifixe is to be worſhipped with the very ſelfe-ſame worſhip, wherewith Christ himſelfe is to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</hi> The difference then betweene the Papiſts and vs, in the doctrine of the worſhip and ſeruice of God, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth both in the manner and the matter of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. In the manner of Gods worſhip, wee vpon iuſt grounds doe varie from them, becauſe that whereas God being a <hi>Spirite,</hi> loueth only ſuch worſhippers, as worſhip him in ſpirite and truth, and to that ende would haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion it ſelfe to be free vnder very ſure and moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt ceremonies of diuine ſeruice, and therefore hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto vs ſome fewe in ſteed of many, and the moſt eaſie to be done,<note place="margin">Iohn: <hi>4, 29.</hi> Aug. de doct. Chri. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> moſt honourable for ſignification, and moſt cleare and pure to bee obſerued. The religion of the Papiſts is ſo loden with ceremonies, preſumptions, &amp; deuiſes of men, that their manner of worſhipping of God in their Temple, is become now altogether Iewiſh and carnall, conſiſting in nothing elſe but altogether in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and ceremoniall exerciſes, in the doctrine whereof, ther is neither faith nor ſpirit, nor any working of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt almoſt required.</p>
            <p>Touching the matter of Gods worſhip, wherein we dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the Papiſts, thus it ſtands, wee teach and hold, that onely God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the holie Ghoſt, are to be worſhipped with diuine honor, and no creature beſides: grounding our ſelues vpon this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and maxime in diuinitie, that adoration is due one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God, and therefore that God onely is to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.<note place="margin">Lu: <hi>4.</hi> Deu: <hi>6.</hi> De vera re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligi. cap. <hi>54.</hi>
               </note> And ſo <hi>S. Augustine</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is very well recorded in the Scriptures, that man was prohibited by an Angel to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip none, but onely God, vnder whom hee himſelfe was a fellowe ſeruant. And therefore hee ſaith; Ecce vnum Deum colo,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14083:27"/> Behold, I worſhip and adore none but God alone.</hi> And thence he deriueth the name of religion, <hi>quòd ei vni religet ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas noſtras,</hi> becauſe it religeth our ſoules onely to him: But the papiſts (as before hath beene alleadged in their ſeruice) ioyne with the worſhip of God, the worſhip of Angels, the worſhip of the Crucifix, the worſhip of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the adoration of the Sacrament of the Altar, as they call it, whereunto they aſcribe diuine honour and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus farre proued vnto you that God and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> cannot both be ſerued together, no more then God and <hi>Dagon</hi> can ſtand together, it remaineth now in the third place that I intreate of the Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> his exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the people wherein he exhorteth to conſtancie in religion and following God.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>3</label> 3. Part.</head>
               <p>Conſtancie, preſeuerance and continuance in the true knowledge of God, are vertues required of all ſuch as intend to lead a godly, and a Chriſtian life, and finally reſolue to finiſh the period of their liues in defence and maintenance of the true religion of Ieſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 24.13. <hi>Reue.</hi> 3.11.</note> 
                  <hi>He that continueth to the end ſhall be ſaued.</hi> Behold ſaith God to the Angell of the Church of <hi>Philadelphia, behold I come ſhortly: behold that which thou haſt, that no man take away thy crowne.</hi> And in the 2. of the Reuelation, thus the ſonne of God ſpeaketh to the reſt of them of <hi>Thiatyra,</hi> which knew not the deepeneſſe of Sathan, <hi>I will put vpon you none other burden, but this, holdfaſt that which you haue vntill I come.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reue.</hi> 2.24.25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23.</note> And the Apoſtle to the Hebrewes giueth vs this aduiſe and counſell, <hi>that we ſhould keepe the profeſſion of our hope without wauering,</hi> ſo that being rooted and grounded in true knowledge, and built vpon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe being the head and chiefe corner ſtone, we ſhould not henceforth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14083:28"/> be children any more wauering and carried about with euery blaſt of doctrine,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.14.</note> by the deceit of men, and with craftineſſe, whereby they lye in waite to deceiue.</p>
               <p>The diuell knowing full well what this hope of our ſaluation is, ceaſeth not continually to bend his force againſt the foundation and fortreſſe of our faith. And ſurely, if Sathan by his principall Miniſters the Ieſuites and Seminarie Prieſts, can once ſhake the ground worke whereon we build our health and Saluation (which is the affiance in Chriſt our God, and credite to his word) if he can but once perſwade vs to retire from that hold and ground we ſtand vpon, as vpon an vnmoueable rocke, then hath he wonne his deſire: then enters he with ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners diſplaied vpon vs, toſſing vs vp &amp; downe with euery blaſt of doctrine, and beateth vs downe to the pit of damnation. For the eaſier compaſſing of this his wicked deſignement, ſome be perſwaded by arguments, and by reaſons to forſake their faith, and ſo by this meanes draweth them to ſundrie hereſies and errours: others he forceth by torments and perſecutions quite to giue ouer their hold: others againe he winneth, and allureth to himſelfe with baites of pleaſures to denie Chriſt: and ſo <hi>Iulian</hi> perceiuing that torments could not preuaile to cauſe the Chriſtians to reuenge their profeſſion, gaue them the greateſt roomes and honours of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, euen as Sathan when he could not by argument ouercome our Sauiour Chriſt, offered him all the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the world, if he would fall downe before him and worſhip him. The onely powerfull meanes to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all the forcible aſſaults of Sathan is, whenſoeuer he offereth vs to runne to the walles of faith, betaking our ſelues each man to his defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as in the certaine truth of gods eternall teſtament.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.15. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.13,</note> Stand faſt, ſaith the Apoſtle to the Theſſalonians, and keepe the traditions, which ye haue beene taught. And to the Corinthians to the ſame purpoſe he ſaith <hi>watch ye, ſtand faſt: and quite your
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14083:28"/> ſelues like men, and be ſtrong. Let the feare of the Lord be vpon you.</hi> Sticke faſt vnto the Lord, and cleaue vnto him with a perpetuall couenant which ſhall neuer be forgotten. Three waies there are whereby we may grow to this reſolution: firſt by remembring the intolerable paines of hell if wee doe reuolt; ſecondly by thinking of the vnſpeakable ioyes of heauen, if wee continue firme: Thirdly looking vpon ſuch who haue ſuffered before vs, and to propoſe them vnto vs for examples of imitation. And ſo to ſhew the like conſtancie in clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto God which they did. We haue recorded in ſcripture the examples of <hi>Dauid;</hi> of the three children, of <hi>Eleazar</hi> and ſundrie others who for the zeale they bare to the religion of their God, were reſolute to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure moſt cruell torments. The Apoſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes mentioneth ſuch, who being ſtrong in faith, when they were tried by racking, yet would not, or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not to be deliuered that they might receiue a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reſurrection.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb</hi> 11.35.</note> We haue againe in the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories, the examples of eighteene hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Chriſtians in the time of the tenne primitiue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions which were done to moſt cruell deaths, onely becauſe they would not forſake their Chriſtian religion. And to come neerer home to our owne daies we haue examples of our owne brethren in Queene Maries daies, who for the zeale they bare to the houſe of God, were content to yeeld their backes to the ſcourge, their neckes to the tormentours, their bodies to the furious flames of fire, their ſoules with ioy into the hands of him that made them. Concerning whom I doubt not, but that euery true member of the Catholike Church, may wiſh from her very heart, <hi>that his ſoule might die the death of thoſe righteous perſons, and that his latter end might be like vnto theirs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is then the exhortation which <hi>Elias</hi> giueth to thoſe wauing and wauering <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> which could not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14083:29"/> reſolue whether God or <hi>Baal</hi> was to be worſhipped, if God be the Lord, follow him, cleaue faſt vnto him, and ſerue him with all the deſire of your hearts: but God is the Lord, yea the onely Lord, therefore he onely is to be worſhipped. It is the Lord onely that formeth the light, and createth the darkeneſſe: it is he that hath made all things, which hath ſpread out the heauens alone, and ſtretched out the earth by himſelfe, it is he that can fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell things before they come to paſſe: it is he alone that can ſay my counſell ſhall ſtand, and whatſoeuer I will haue come to paſſe, ſhall come to paſſe: it is he that brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth Princes to nothing, and maketh the iudges of the earth as vanitie: yea it is the euerlaſting God that hath created the ends of the earth, and bringeth out all their armies by numbers, and calleth them all by their names: And therefore he onely is the Lord.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Baal,</hi> if he be a God, let him plead for himſelfe againſt him that caſt downe his Altar,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudi.</hi> 6.31.</note> ſaith <hi>Ioas</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Gideon,</hi> after that his ſonne had deſtroyed the Altar of <hi>Baal,</hi> and cut downe the groue that was by it. <hi>Baal</hi> can giue you nothing: he can doe neither good nor euill, and therefore he is no god: though a man cry vnto him, yet cannot he anſwere him, nor deliuer him out of his tribulation and therefore he is no God.</p>
               <p>The Papiſts are much grieued with vs, becauſe we will not acknowledge the Sacrament of the Altar to be our Lord, and our God, and thereupon caſt this vniuſt aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vpon vs, and falſely charge vs, that <hi>We call the bodie of Chriſt an abominable idoll.</hi> True it is indeed that we call that an abominable idoll. Which they terme the body of Chriſt, and vnder that pretence fall downe before it to worſhip it, and call it <hi>Lord and God,</hi> in doing whereof what other thing doe they but make a God of a peece of bread, and vnder the name of the bodie of Chriſt, ſet vp an Idoll in the Church of God. But as for the bodie of Chriſt wee haue euermore confeſſed with <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> that it is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14083:29"/> 
                  <hi>worthie of the higheſt honour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor: Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil.</hi> 14.</note> as being inſeparablie ioyned to his God-heade in one perſon, ſitting now at the right hand of God: and wee adore it, and worſhip it, euen as the bodie of the ſonne of God: not onely for the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of an hand, as the Papiſts vſe to do, while the prieſt is able to hold vp the Sacrament, and that with doubt of our ſelues whether wee doe well or no, which thing is vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly vncomfortable, and dangerous, and full of terrours to the conſcience: but we worſhip that bleſſed and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious bodie, as that bleſſed Martyr <hi>S. Stephen</hi> did, being in heauen, at the right hand of the power of God, and therefore without doubt or danger; and that at all times, and for euer: and we belieue, and thus wee teach, that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, euen in the nature and ſubſtance of our fleſh, is the Lord in the glorie of God the Father.</p>
               <p>Howbeit we ſay Chriſts bodie is one thing, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment another. The Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is an earthly thing, Chriſts bodie an heauenly thing: the Sacrament is corruptible, Chriſts bodie is glorious: the Sacrament is receiued into our bodies, Chriſts body is only receiued into our ſoules, and entreth not into our bodies.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Luke</hi> reporteth how that the Diſciples of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abaſhed at Chriſtes ſuddaine preſence among them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk:</hi> 24 38.39.</note> and through feare, ſuppoſing they had ſeene a ſpirite or Ghoſt, our Sauiour ſpake vnto them in this manner: <hi>Why are yee troubled? and wherefore doe doubts ariſe in your hearts? behold mine handes and my feete, for it is I my ſelfe: handle mee, and ſee me: for a ſpirite hath not fleſh and bones as yee ſee me haue;</hi> and ſo ſhewed them both his hands and his feete. Euen ſo verily, the Sacrament it ſelfe, if it could ſpeake, would ſpeake in this manner, at the time of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuation to the ſtanders by: why doe ſuch thoughts ariſe in your harts, as to thinke that I am your Lord and God? Why ſtand ye thus gazing, thus knocking your breaſts, and bending your knees to me. Handle me, taſte me, and looke vpon me, and ſee whether I haue not all the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14083:30"/> properties of true bread: that is, whether I haue not the very forme, ſhape, ſauour, ſmell, colour, and weight of bread. As for the bodie of Chriſt, it cannot bee bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with hands, or grated with teeth, or conueied into the bellie, as you ſee that I am. The bread of life cannot be felt, ſeene, or taſted, or diſcerned by any outward ſence, as you ſee that I am: and therefore belieue them not which teach you otherwiſe, for I am bread, I am no God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Quarta Pars.</head>
               <p>Hauing thus farre ſpoken of the exhortation of the Prophet <hi>Elias,</hi> wherein hee exhorteth them to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in religion, and conſtant in the confeſſion of him, which is the onely true God: it remaineth now in the laſt place to ſhewe vnto you, what the ſucceſſe was, which inſued vpon the Prophets reproofe, which at the firſt was thus, that the people anſwered him not a word, ſtanding in doubt, whether hee were the onely God or no. But a little afterwards, when they ſaw how miraculouſlie <hi>the fire of the Lord fell, and conſumed the burnt offering, and the wood, and the ſtones, and the dust, and licked vp the water which was in the ditch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>King:</hi> 18.38.</note> being moued with this ſtrange and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous worke of God, they were ſodainly changed in their opinions, and falling on their faces, cryed out, <hi>the Lord is God, the Lord is God:</hi> Where we may ſee, that howſoeuer it may be, that God permitteth his owne people for ſome certaine time, to fall into manie dangerous errours, yet ſuch is his great mercie towards them, that firſt or laſt he calleth them home againe, and will not ſuffer them final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to periſh, as here hee dealt with his owne people of <hi>Iſraell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is no one thing more commonly obiected by Papiſts againſt the religion of the Proteſtants, then that, as they ſay, wee haue no miracles in our church. If your Church be the true church, if the doctrine you teach be
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14083:30"/> the true Catholike faith of Chriſt, where bee your mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, (ſay they) and where bee thoſe ſignes and wonders among you, which may proue vnto vs, that your religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is of God?</p>
               <p>To the which objection I anſwere with Chryſoſtome,<note place="margin">Opere imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto. Hom: <hi>49.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that there was a time wherein of olde it was knowne by miracles, who were true Christians, who were falſe, and where a man might finde the true Church of God indeede:</hi> but now ſaith hee, <hi>the working of miracles is quite taken away, and is rather found among them that are falſe Chriſtians.</hi> Which ſpeech of that learned father is truely verified this day in the church of Antichriſt, where the Papiſts can make their Croſſes to ſpeake, their Idolles to goe, their images to weepe, to ſweate, to laugh, to ſhift themſelues from place, to light their owne lamps: Yea, the vnholy fathers of the ſocietie of Ieſus, to ſet a glorious countenance of their miracles, tell vs in great ſadnes, that with their holie-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they haue calmed the Sea, chaſed away mice out of the countrey, and haue made barren women to conceiue, and beare children. But againſt ſuch miracle-mongers, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine, My God hath armed mee,</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">Tractat: in Ioh: <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>in the latter dayes there ſhall ariſe falſe Prophets, working ſignes and wonders, to deceiue the very Elect of God, if it were poſſible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>True it is, the Apoſtles wrought miracles, but it was thereby to confirme the Goſpel, they preached, as the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt writeth, <hi>The Lord wrought with them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar:</hi> 16.20</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; confirmed the word with ſignes that followed.</hi> And the Apoſt: to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues likewiſe ſaith, <hi>that ſaluation at the firſt bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by the Lord, &amp; was confirmed vnto vs by them that heard him</hi> (meaning the Apoſtles) bearing <hi>witnes thereunto with ſignes &amp; wonders, &amp; with diuers gifts of the holy Ghoſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb:</hi> 2.3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will.</hi> In the firſt beginning then, and gathering of the church, miracles were neceſſarie. But as when wee goe about to plant a tree, ſo long we water it, vntill we ſee it hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> root, but when it is once ſubſtantially groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and branches ſpread abroad, wee take no more paine
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14083:31"/> to water it. So likewiſe, as long as the people of the world were altogether faithleſſe, this meanes of miracles for confirmation of doctrine, was of Indulgence graunted then. But when once ſpirituall inſtruction had taken better place, the corporall ſignes ſurceaſed ſtraight. The kingdome and Church of Chriſt was planted in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of doctrine and miracles by the power of the holie Ghoſt. Now therefore it is againſt faith, if any looke for miracles againe to confirme the Goſpell, which is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſo confirmed, that if an <hi>Angell from heauen,</hi> ſhould preach vnto vs any otherwiſe, then that which hath bene preached vnto vs, let him be accurſed. Seeing then the doctrine this day taught, profeſſed, and preached in the Church of England, is the verie ſame doctrine which Chriſt himſelfe deliuered to his Apoſtles, and they, to their aftercommers, there needeth no other confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by miracles to be wrought by vs.</p>
               <p>Thus haue I with what perſpicuitie and breuitie the proportion of the time allotted vnto mee would permit, runne ouer this portion of holy ſcripture. The Lorde giue a bleſſing vnto the wordes which you haue heard this day with your outward eares out of my mouth, and by the ſecret working of his holy ſpirite, giue ſuch force vnto them, that they may become fruitfull in the hearts of you all. And foraſmuch as the Lord in theſe Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, and happie dayes of ours, hath dealt with vs in farre greater mercie, then hee hath done with any other nation beſides, in that wee haue of his great clemencie theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares together enioyed with libertie of bodie, and freedome of conſcience, the greateſt ioy and felicitie that euer betided any people, euen the ſincere preaching of his moſt ſacred word and Goſpell, with the right and due adminiſtration of his Sacraments, with health, peace, libertie, and quietneſſe, vnder the wiſe, godly, and moſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14083:31"/> peaceable gouernment of his choſen ſeruant <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> our late Queene and Miſtriſſe, &amp; now at this time vnder the gouernement of our moſt gracious Soueraign Lord <hi>King Iames,</hi> whoſe life the Lord preſerue, and long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue among vs: that conſidering how the Lord hath multiplied his graces, and bleſſings vpon vs, that we may euermore continue conſtant and ſtedfaſt in the profeſſion of his eternall truth, that what oppoſition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we find in the world of fawning flatterie or perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting crueltie, that we neuer ſuffer our ſelues to be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the ſame, but that we may ſtriue for the truth euen to death, holding faſt that which we haue vntill the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: that we neuer halt or double in matter of religion, nor waue betweene two opinions, but that wee may ſtedfaſtly cleaue vnto the Lord all the daies of our life, that wee neuer admit any fellowſhip, or communion with the Church of Rome, knowing that the whole religion of poperie, wherein it differeth from vs, is nothing elſe but a moſt wicked apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie from the ancient faith. So that being confirmed and ſtrengthened, and eſtabliſhed in that Goſpel, which hath beene preached vnto vs, which we haue receiued, wherein we continue, and which is able to ſaue vs, we may euery day more and more, grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord, and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, to the which Chriſt Ieſus, together with the father, and the holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed all power, glory, dominion, and Maieſtie, both now and euermore; Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
